声音检查，大家能听到我说话吗？
Sound check, can everybody hear me?
是的。好的，
Yep, yep. Okay okay,
欢迎收听 6.S081
so welcome to the next lecture
的下一节课，
in the 6.S081, wherever you
无论你在哪里，
are, particular,
我希望西海岸，
I hope that the folks on
佛罗里达和
the west coast or in Florida
阿拉巴马州的人们都还好，
and Alabama do OK, you know, all
那里糟糕的情况会好起来。
the terrible circumstances there.
嗯，那么，
Um, so,
今天的话题是
um, the topic for today,
虚拟内存，
is virtual memory, particularly we're
特别是我们要讲的页表，
going to talk about page tables
我们多次讲到
we'll return to this topic
这个话题，
few times,
有多次关于
there will be multiple
这个的讲座。
[] lectures.
一开始，
Maybe just start off and,
我们会再次开始
you know, get our question and answer
我们的问答环节，
going again,
我想问
I would like to ask you
一些问题，
a little bit,
你对 6.004 或
what do you remember from，
6.033 的讲的
about virtual memory from 6.004
虚拟内存
maybe from 6.033,
有什么印象。
if you're taking that.
我要告诉你们，
I'll tell you, my own sort
我自己对虚拟内存的看法，
of view on virtual memory,
这就是当我
which is when I took it,
第一次了解它的时候，
to first learned about it,
还是个学生的时候，
learned about it as
我认为
a student, I thought it
它很简单，很直接，
was pretty straightforward,
你知道的，
you know how hard could
它能有多难，
it be,
就是一个将虚拟地址
it's a table that maps virtual
映射到物理地址的表。
addresses to physical addresses.
你知道，
You know, maybe a
可能有一点复杂，
little more complicated,
但没有那么复杂。
but you know not that
只有当你实际
complicated, only when you start
用它来编程的时候，
programming with it.
我真的知道了，
I should really learn, virtual
虚拟内存是巧妙的，迷人的，
memory is tricky and fascinating,
而且非常强大。
and very powerful.
所以，
So, hopefully in the
希望在接下来的几节课，
next couple of lectures, in
接下来的几个实验中，
the next couple of labs,
你们能从这个角度
you'll know appreciate
理解虚拟内存。
virtual memory from that perspective.
我们将提问
We will ask a couple
在线的的几个人，
people here are online, you know
关于你对
what do you remember about virtual
6.004 或 6.033
memory from either 6.004 or
虚拟内存的印象是什么。
6.033 taking it.
我要叫几个名字，
Again, I'm just gonna call some
你知道，
names and you know,
分享你的印象。
share your memories. About the
Adela Yang.
抱歉，问题是什么？
Sorry, what's the question? What
你对
do you remember about
6.004 或
virtual memory from maybe 6.004
6.033
or 6.033
的虚拟内存有什么印象？
if you have taken that.
它使用
It uses like, offset to save
偏移量来记录
on like, remembering virtual address
虚拟地址到物理地址的映射。
to physical address mappings.
好的，下一个， Abrams Caldera 。
OK, how about Abrams Caldera.
Abrams ，你在线吗？
Abrams, are you online?
是的，我的印象是
Yeah, my memory is that
它使用，
it uses like,
就像通过
it's a way of one protecting
一种[]表示
the physical hardware by
来保护物理硬件，
kind of [] representation of
然后，
it and then you just
你使用一些
have some virtual address things like,
至少 44 位的虚拟地址，
at least 44 bit, that map
来映射一些物理地址，
some physical address,
这些物理地址
that's usually I think 16
通常是 64 位的。
bits were in fact.
好的，下一个， Bibic Pendant 。
Okay, good, how about Bibic Pendant.
我记得的是，
What I remember was,
你可以让
um, you can have
每个进程有一个
each process has a separate
单独的地址空间。
address space.
还有，
And,
可以使用内存管理单元
the memory management unit or I
或者一些其他技术
mean some other technique can be
来映射，
used to map,
将每个进程
the virtual addresses of the
地址空间的
address space of each of the
虚拟地址转换为
processes to the physical,
物理地址。
physical address.
还有，虚拟地址的
And the virtual address, the
最后几位
lower bits
是相同的，
are kind of the same,
因此，
so that,
映射是以块为单位的，
the the mapping is in blocks,
这有助于提高性能。
which helps with performance.
Wiseley Wu.
是的，
Yeah, I guess what I
我印象最深的是
remember most is that virtual address
虚拟地址允许我们
allows us to,
保护物理地址
yeah, protect physical addresses from
不受每个进程的影响。
each process.
我们可以使用
And we can use some clever
一些巧妙的操作，
manipulation, so that the bits that
这样对应于物理地址的位
correspond to the physical address can
也可以
be used somehow in the virtual
在虚拟地址中使用。
addresses as well.
Wilson Spearmen.
是的，我记得
Yeah, I remember it's really fundamental
这是隔离的基础，
to isolation,
因为每个进程都
because every process can basically pretend
可以假装
that it has its own
它有自己的内存可以使用。
sort of memory to use.
很好，很清楚，
Good good well so clearly,
很棒，
that's awesome,
显然，这里有两个主题，
the clear, two themes here
一个是
correct, one is you know
有某种形式的映射，
there's some form of mapping and
这种映射有助于
the mapping is helpful in sort
实现某种程度的隔离，
of achieving isolation,
这正是我们讨论
this is exactly the reason, we're
虚拟内存隔离的原因。
talking about virtual memory isolation.
因此，
So, what
我们在接下来的
we'll see is that in
几节课中会看到，
the next, in the next couple of lectures,
特别是，当我们开始
in particular, when we start programming
使用虚拟内存编程时，
with virtual memory,
我们会真正深入了解
really get an in-depth understanding
它的力量。
of what its power is.
为了让你理解，
And, so to get a
你知道，
sense, that you know, this is
这是第一节课，
the first lecture and mostly focusing
内容主要集中在虚拟内存的机制上，
on the mechanisms for virtual memory,
稍后我们可以看到，
and then later we can see
如何使用这些机制来实现
how we can use these mechanisms
那些很棒的技巧。
to achieve, you know, cool tricks.
所以
So the topic for today, or
今天的话题或议程是，
agenda for today, the plan
计划分为三部分。
is sort of three part.
首先，
First, I'm going to talk about the
我要谈谈地址空间，
address spaces, as some of you
你们中有些人也提到这个。
mentioning in your.
这正是我们需要的。
Just what we need.
刚才回答问题的时候
Just mentioned just briefly mentioned,
简单提了一下，
in response to the question,
我还要讲一下
I'm going to talk about the
分页硬件。
paging hardware paging hardware.
当然，
And I'm going to focus of
我将重点介绍
course on the paging hardware of
RISC-V 的分页硬件。
the RISC-V.
但是基本上每个处理器，
But basically every processor, modern processor
现代处理器都有
has some form of paging hardware
某种形式的分页硬件。
sort of,
实际上它是
if you will, the
支持虚拟内存的
default mechanism for actually
默认机制。
supporting virtual memory.
然后，
And then,
课程的最后一部分
the last part of
将介绍一些
the lecture is going to
xv6 的
walk through some xv6
虚拟内存代码。
virtual memory code.
还有，内核地址空间和
And, layout of kernel address space and
用户地址空间的布局。
user address spaces.
所以这是主要的计划。
So that's the main plan.
好的，那么
Okay, so,
如果我们回答，
if we answers, you know, []
你所提到的[]，
you mentioned,
回答这个问题，
in response to this question,
你知道，
you know,
有虚拟内存的一个驱动力
one driving reason to have
是因为
virtual memory is because you can
你可以用它来实现隔离，
use it to achieve isolation,
如果页表设置正确，
if you set up the page
并且编程正确，
tables correctly and program them correctly,
那么原则上
then you can in principle
就可以实现强隔离。
achieve strong isolation.
这再次提醒我们，
And so this is to remind us again,
我们想从隔离中
you know what we want with
得到什么，
from isolation,
比如，
let's say, you know a
你知道一张标准图片，
standard picture,
我们有一些用户应用程序，
we have some user applications
比如 shell ，
like shell,
cat ，还有
you know cat, you know, all the util
你在实验一中构建的
things, that you've built in
所有实用工具，
lab one, and we have
我们还有内核，内核在下面，
the kernel, the kernel sitting below,
操作系统在
the operating system sitting in
内核空间里。
kernel space.
你知道，
And you know what we like
我们要做的是
to do is sort of have
把这些应用程序框起来，
you know boxes around these
这样它们
applications, so that they can't
就不会真正相互影响，
really affect each other and similar
类似的，我们希望它们
we want them to be completely
完全独立于内核和操作系统，
independent of the kernel,
这样即使
the operating system, so that if
一个应用程序做了
an application does something either accidentally
一些意外或恶意的事情，
bad or maliciously bad,
也不会
that doesn't really affect the
真正影响操作系统。
operating system.
这就是我们的目标，
So that's our goal and the
今天我们关注的
particular aspect of the problem that
具体方面是
we want to focus on today
内存方面的问题，
is the memory side of things,
所以我们关注的是
so we really want to
内存隔离。
focus on memory isolation.
默认情况下，
And by default,
如果我们什么都不做，
if we don't do anything,
我们就没有内存隔离，
we don't really have memory isolation,
因为如果你想一下，
because if you think about
这有一个 RISC-V 板，
it, there's going to be one
就是我上周给你们
RISC-V board that I showed
展示的那个，
you last week,
它有一个内存，
it has a memory,
一堆 DRAM 芯片，
a bunch of DRAM chips,
在 DRAM 芯片中
and the in the DRAM
存储着
chips, the code for
这些应用程序的代码，
these applications
内存中的
is stored, somewhere in memory
某个地方是内核，文本数据堆栈或其他，
is the kernel, text data stack
如果 shell 正在运行，
everything, somewhere in memory used to
内存中的某个地方是 shell ，
shell if the shell is running,
还有某个地方是 cat 程序。
somewhere in memory the cat program.
只有一个物理内存，
So, there's one physical memory,
从 0 开始，
you know starting from zero to
到一个大地址，
big, big address,
它取决于机器
depending how much memory we
有多少内存，
have, really have in our
在这个物理内存中，
machine and in that physical
所有这些程序都必须存在。
memory all these programs must be present.
否则，你知道，
Otherwise, you know, the processor
处理器甚至不能执行它们的指令。
can't even execute their instructions.
这就是风险所在，
This is what the risk, you
在这里很明显，
know clearly here is, that let's
比如，举个简单的例子，
say, let's make a little bit
比如 shell ，
simplistic, let's say the shell,
位于地址 0 到 200 ，
you know sits for
应该是 2000 ，
address 0 to address 200,
1000 到 2000 。
two thousand, 1000 to 2000.
假设，
And let's say you know,
cat 有一个
you know whatever cat has a
编程错误，
programming error,
它加载某个东西到寄存器 a0 中。
it loads, you know, in register a0.
假设，加载的是 1000 ，
Let's say, loads the 1000
地址对应于
address basically corresponding to the
shell 的起始地址，
start of the shell and then
然后意外地
you know by accident,
执行了 sd $7, (a0) 指令。
executes the instruction 'sd $7, (a0)'.
这条指令的作用是，
Which has the effect of that,
将值 7 写到
basically it writes the value 7
地址 1000 ，
to the address 1000 and so
所以
it would be scribbling over, you
它会修改
know the basically the memory image,
属于 shell 的内存镜像。
that belongs to shell.
因此，
And so,
我们肯定不会，
we're certainly not, certain
这肯定会打破隔离，
would break isolation, and be
是我们不想要的。
quite undesirable.
所以我们想要，
And so we want something that
从根本上把不同程序的
basically really separates these memories from
内存隔离起来，
the different programs from each other,
让这样的事情不会发生。
so that things like that just cannot happen.
要做到这一点，
So one way, to do that,
有一种方法是，
is an idea that's you
叫做地址空间的方法。
know typically called address spaces.
基本思路很简单，
And the basic idea is straightforward,
我们想要做的基本上
what we wanna do, is basically
是给包括内核在内的每个应用程序，
give every application including the kernel,
它自己的地址空间。
its own address space.
所以我们像下面这样思考，
And so we can think about
我们运行 cat ，
this like, we use cat running,
它有一个从 0 开始
you know, it has an address
到最大值的
space starting at 0, you know
地址空间，
to whatever maximum value, you know
shell 也运行在一个地址空间，
shell run has an address space, its
它自己的地址空间，
own address space,
也从地址 0 开始
also starting at address 0,
到某个地址，
going to some value,
内核也有
you know the kernel has
它自己的地址空间。
its own address space.
也就是操作系统
OS has its own
有自己的地址空间。
address space.
所以，
And so,
让我们回到
one example when cat you know
刚才使用 cat 的例子，
refers to, we go back to
像上一张讲稿中
our example of the previous slide
做的那样，
where we did,
对于指令 'st 7, (a0)' ,
whatever 'st 7, (a0)',
假设 a0 中的值是 1000 。
and let's say in a0, there's value 1000.
你知道如果 cat
You know if cat execute
执行这条指令，
the instruction,
它会写地址 1000 ，
it will write to the address 1000,
但这是它自己的地址 1000 ，
but it is its own address 1000,
而不是，
it's not,
shell 的地址 1000 。
the address of the 1000 of the shell.
所以基本上，每个程序
So basically, every program runs with
都有自己的地址空间，
its own address space, has its
有自己的值，
own value and those addresses are
并且这些地址是完全独立的。
completely independent.
你知道，这个
You know this notion of
不同地址空间的概念，
different address spaces,
cat 甚至不能
cat doesn't really have an ability to
访问实际上
even refer to an address, that
属于 shell 的地址。
actually belongs to the shell.
所以这就是
And so that sort of the
我们想要达到
game that were the end goal
的最终目标，
that we'd like to achieve, because
因为它提供了强隔离，
it's going to provide us with
因为你知道，
strong isolation, because you know it's
cat 不可能
just not possible for cat to
引用任何
refer to any other memory that
不属于它的内存。
is not, you know, its own.
因此，我们现在的目标
And so, our goal now basically
是解决如何
sort of figure out how to
在单个物理内存上
multiplex if you will all these
复用这些
different address bases on a single
不同的地址，
physical memory,
因为根本上，
because in the end,
我们只有一堆 DRAM 芯片。
we only have a bunch of DRAM chips.
你知道，
were you know, ram
RAM 芯片是内存使用的。
chips were the memories locate.
所以，我的计划是。
And so, um, and so I sort of plan.
好的，Amiar ，
Okay, yeah, Amiar,
你有什么问题，说吧。
you have a question, go ahead.
我想知道，
So I'm wondering,
在物理硬件的
in the configuration of the
配置中，
physical hardware,
只有这么大的空间，
there's only so much space and
而在虚拟内存布局中，
the virtual memory layout,
也有一个最大地址，
there's also a max virtual address,
从设计上来说，虚拟地址对于物理地址
by design is the virtual address
是否要足够小。
made to be small enough.
不，不需要，
No, not necessarily,
虚拟地址空间
you know the virtual address
可能比
space could be bigger than
物理内存大，
the physical memory,
物理内存也可能比
the physical memory could be bigger
虚拟地址空间大，
than the virtual address space
我们很快就会看到
and we'll see in a second
这一切是如何发生的，
how it all can happen and
它实际上会[]，
it's actually going to []
就像我们将在页表中看到的那样，
about, as we'll see with page tables,
这是非常灵活的。
that's extremely flexible.
那么，
So, is it, is it
有没有可能，
possible that like the physical
就像物理内存耗尽一样，
memory gets exhausted,
因为这么多进程
because so many processes use
使用了自己的虚拟空间。
all their virtual space.
是的，这当然是可能的，
Yeah, that's certainly possible and we'll
我们很快会看到，
see in the second, how,
例如，你知道，
for example you know you have
有一堆大型应用程序，
a bunch of big applications that
每个应用程序都有很大的页表，
each have big page tables,
它们分配了很多内存，
they allocate a lot of memory,
有些时候
you know some point you run
内存就会用完。
out of memory.
我明白了，
I see,
谢谢。那么，有没有人知道
thanks. And so where does this
这在 xv6 中哪里用到了？
show up xv6, anybody.
你肯定
You, you sure,
在目前做的
touched on a little bit
syscall 实验中
in the syscall lab, that
用到了一点，
you're currently doing,
分配页面的位置。
where page is allocated.
或者，你做的 syscall 实验，
Or, you do the syscall lab,
在 syscall 实验的一部分
you finished it in one
完成了它，
part of the syscall lab,
打印有多少空闲内存地址。
printing how much free memory address.
Kalloc ？是的，kalloc ，
Kalloc? Yeah, kalloc, right,
kalloc ，有空闲页的列表，
for kalloc, have a list of free pages,
如果这个列表
if that list of free pages
在某一时刻为空或用完。
is empty or runs out at some point.
然后， kalloc 将返回
Then, you know, kalloc is going
一个空指针，
to return a null pointer, and
希望操作系统能做一些明智的事情，
hopefully the operation system does something sensible,
把消息传回给用户应用程序，
that basically propagated back to the
告诉应用程序，
user application saying like well, you
没有更多的内存给你，
know no more memory for you
或者任何人都没有更多的内存。
or no more memory in total, nobody.
好的？操作系统只需要做一项工作
Ok? Then just a job for OS
就可以很好地处理这些情况，
to handle those cases gracefully where
将错误消息
basically generally means propagating an error
传回到用户应用程序。
message to user application.
好的，很好。
Okay, good.
那么如何实现
So how do you implement these
这些地址空间，
address spaces,
如何在单个物理内存中
you know how basically multiplex
复用所有
all these address spaces across a
这些地址空间，
single physical memory and the most
最常用的并且非常灵活的方法
common approach and a very flexible
就是使用页表。
approach is to use pagetables.
这个想法是，
The idea is,
这是一项艰苦的工作支持，
this is a hard work support,
这是由处理器
so this is implemented in hardware
在硬件中实现的，或者
by the processor or by a
称为内存管理单元（MMU），
unit called the memory management unit,
所以你应该想到的画面是，
so the picture that you should
你知道，
have your head is, you know, the CPU
执行指令的 CPU ，
that executes instructions, whatever are,
无论是什么指令，
you know, are store instruction that
比如存储指令， sd $7, (a0) ，
was you know 'sd $7, (a0)',
也执行这些类型的指令，
also executes those kind of
你知道
instructions and you know when
当它执行 store 指令，
it executes one of their
load 指令，
store instruction, load instruction,
无论任何指令实际上
whatever anything that actually has
都包含一个地址。
an address.
那个地址，
You know, that address we're going
我们要把它
to think about it as
当成一个虚拟地址，
a virtual address,
它不是一个物理地址，
so it's not a physical address,
而是一个虚拟地址。
it's a virtual address.
例如，
And so,
我们在这里使用的
for example the value in a0
a0 中的值，
that we're using here,
假设它是 1000 ，
yeah, say that's 1000,
这个 0x1000 是一个虚拟地址，
0x1000 data is a
虚拟地址基本上
virtual address and virtual addresses basically
是通过所谓的
routed through something what's called
内存管理单元路由的，
the memory management unit,
并且内存管理单元将其
and the memory manager unit
转换成物理地址。
translates into a physical address.
然后这个物理地址
And that physical address then was
实际上指向内存。
actually used to index into memory.
加载值或
And load whatever value or
存储需要写入的任何值。
store whatever value needs to be written there.
所以从 CPU 的
And so the CPU from
角度来看，
the CPU point of view,
它总是发出，
it always issues,
一旦 MMU 启用，
every instruction that issues,
它发出的每条指令
once the MMU use, enabled
都使用了虚拟地址。
our virtual addresses.
为了将这些虚拟地址
And to translate these virtual addresses
转换成物理地址，基本上，
to physical addresses, basically,
MMU 有一个表。
MMU has a table.
这个表中，
And you know virtual address
虚拟地址在一边，
on one side, physical address
物理地址在另一边，
on one side,
例如，
the other side, for example here is
这里是我们的 1000 的条目，
our entry for 1000 and maybe
可能映射到任何，
that maps to whatever,
你知道， 0x （开头的）
you know, 0x whatever you're
无论什么东西，
making something up with like
比如某个值，
something value,
在物理内存中的某个地方。
somewhere in physical memory.
所以这个在虚拟和物理之间的映射，
So this mapping between virtual and
它相当灵活。
physical, it's quite flexible.
因此，
And so on one side,
在一侧是虚拟地址，
we have the virtual address
在另一侧的是
of the other side of
物理地址。
the physical addresses.
通常，这个映射
Typically, you know this mapping itself
也存储在内存中。
is also stored in memory.
所以 CPU 有一些
And so the CPU has some
寄存器，
register that basically points to,
寄存器包含
that contains the physical
存储页表的物理地址，
address of where the page table is stored
在这里，
somewhere, in basically the page
页表或映射
table or just map somewhere stored
存储在物理内存中。
in physical memory.
比方说，你知道，
Let's say, you know,
地址 10 ，
whatever, address 10,
在 RISC-V 上
basically this register which is
这个寄存器是 satp 。
called on the RISC-V satp.
你知道存储着地址 10 ，
You know stores the address 10
因此， CPU 可以
and so, that the CPU
告诉内存管理单元
can tell the memory manager units
在哪里查找映射，
where to find, you know, basically the map
这个映射将虚拟地址
to actually translate virtual to
转换为物理地址。
physical addresses.
然后，基本的想法
And then the basic idea
是给每个应用程序
is to give every application
提供它自己的映射。
it's own map.
所以 cat 有它的映射。
So cat is going to have it's map.
所以每一个映射，有它自己的……。
So every map, it's own...
是的，[Big Ben]，继续。
Yeah, [Big Ben], go ahead.
那么 MMU ，
So the MMU,
你说它不需要
you said it doesn't necessarily store
存储映射。
the mapping.
所以它只是，
So does it just,
只是做转换，
just do the translation like
就像它会读取内存
it will read the memory
并进行转换，
and do the translation,
但不需要
but not necessarily
存储映射。
store the mappings.
这正是你头脑中
That's exactly the right picture that
应该有的的图像。
you should have your head.
但是每个映射，
But every map, okay, so the
所以映射存储在内存中，
map itself stored memory,
MMU 只是
the MMU just basically walks or
访问或查看映射，
looks into the map and we'll
我们很快就会看到，
see in a second, you know,
映射比我在这里画的
the map is slightly more complicated
稍微复杂一些。
than I just draw here.
所以每个应用
So every app has
都有自己的映射。
its own, its own map.
这个映射定义了
Right, and that map basically defines
它的地址空间。
its address space.
因此，当使用 CPU 或
And so when with the CPU or
当操作系统将 CPU
when the operating system switches the
从一个应用程序切换到
CPU from one process from one
另一个应用程序时，
application to another application,
它还切换该 satp 寄存器
it also switches the content
的内容
of this satp register to store
以存储对应进程的
the root of the map of
映射的根地址。
the appropriate process.
因此，通过这种方式，
And so in that way,
你知道在 CPU 上
basically you know multiple applications to
运行多个应用程序，
run on the
每次我们
CPU, every time we switch
从一个应用程序切换到
between from one application to the
下一个应用程序时，
next application,
我们还会切换 satp 寄存器
we also switch the satp
以指向该应用程序
register to point to the appropriate
对应的映射。
map for that application.
通过这种方式，
And in that way,
cat 虚拟地址
basically, virtual addresses you know
与 shell 虚拟地址
for cat are translated differently,
的转换不同，
than the virtual addresses for the
因为每个应用程序
shell, because you know each one
都有自己的映射。
of them has their own map.
理解了吗？
That makes sense?
好的，
Okay, so we, this is the
这是基本的计划，
basic plan and the way I've
到目前为止，我画的或者将要解释的方式，
drawn or gonna explain it so
是相当幼稚的，
far it's pretty naive,
也是不合理的。
and unreasonable.
是的，大卫，说吧。
Yeah, David, go ahead.
很抱歉，
I'm sorry,
你说的 satp 寄存器
so, the you said the
因为进程修改了，
satp register gets modified
我想
for the process, I am guessing
每个进程的
the value of for
satp 寄存器的值
satp register for each process
都是由内核存储的。
is stored by the kernel.
是的，
Yes yes,
内核写入 satp 寄存器，
the kernel is writing satp register,
实际上写入或读取，
in fact writing or reading,
特别是写入 satp 寄存器
particular writing the satp register is
是特权指令。
a privilege instruction.
因此，用户应用程序不能
So user application cannot just
更新页面映射寄存器，
update the page map register, and
然后说我现在要
say like I want to run
使用此页面映射运行。
with this page map now.
因为，那会违反隔离性。
Because, that would violate isolation.
所以它只有内核，
So it's only the kernel, only
只有内核模式下的代码
code in kernel mode can actually
才能真正更新它。
update it.
我明白了。
I see.
好的，正如我所说的，
Okay, so as I said this
这张图片相当幼稚，
picture is pretty naive,
你知道，有一件事
you know one thing I
我没有真正说过
haven't really said anything about how
这个映射是如何工作的。
this actually map works.
而且，我画的方式
And, you know the way I've
似乎表明，
drawn out seems to indicate a
每个虚拟地址，
basically for every virtual address,
在映射上都有一个条目。
you have an entry in the map.
如果你这么做了，
And if you do that,
那么在 RISC-V 上，映射会有多大呢？
how big would that be on RISC-V.
有人回答吗， RISC-V 理论上
Anybody, how many addresses are there on
有多少地址，
the RISC-V in principle, or
或者有多大，
how big, how many addresses go
寄存器可以存储多少地址。
to registers store.
寄存器是 64 位宽，
Registers are 64 bit wide,
那么有多少个地址呢？
so how many addresses.
有人吗？我知道，
Anybody, I know, so insulting your
问这些问题是对你智力的侮辱。
intelligence by asking these questions about.
我们在聊天中有一些答案，
We have some answers in the
是 2 的 64 次方。
chat, like two to the 64.
我没看到聊天内容，抱歉，
I didn't see the chat, sorry,
是的，2 的 64 次方。
yeah, two to 64. Lets see
让我们看看是否能把芯片拿出来，
if I can actually pop off the chip,
这样我就能看到它了。
so I could see it.
是的， 2 的 64 次方，谢谢。
Yeah, two to 64, thank you.
好的，那么这张表会很大。
Alright, so this table would be gigantic.
事实上，我们知道
In fact, we know
只有这张表就会
all memory would be consumed
消耗掉所有的内存，
by just having the table
所以这是不合理的。
so that seems unreasonable.
所以事实上，
And so in fact you
事情不是这样的。
know that's not how things work.
实际上，
In fact, going to
在 RISC-V 中，
in two steps, to actually, how
它的工作分为两个步骤。
it actually works in RISC-V.
第一步是
Step one is don't play
不按地址，
the game per address,
而是按页面操作。
but do per page.
所以一次
So you translate a page at
转换一页， RISC-V 上的
a time and a page
一页是 4 千字节。
on RISC-V is 4 kilobytes.
它是 4096 字节。
Which is a four, 4096 bytes.
这很常见，
This is pretty common,
几乎所有处理器
almost all processors, you know, use
都使用大约 4 千字节的页面大小，
roughly page size 4 kilobytes, or support
或者支持 4 千字节的页面大小。
page size 4 kilobytes.
所以现在，
And so now again, translation works
转换的工作略有不同，
slightly differently,
在这里，我们有虚拟地址。
so if here, we have our virtual address.
惊讶的是，我们将其一分为二，
Amazingly, we split it in two pieces,
一个索引和一个偏移量。
an index and an offset.
偏移量就是
And so the offset is basically
在页面中的字节。
the byte within the page.
因此，当我们，
And so when we do,
当 MMU 进行转换时，
when the MMU does
它会获取索引，
the translation it takes the index,
索引到映射中，
indexes into the map that
给出一些在内存中
gives you some physical page number,
的物理页号。
you know in memory.
物理页号指向
The physical page number that
4096 字节的某个物理页。
points to some physical page of 4096 bytes.
然后是偏移量部分，
And then the offset part,
索引到该物理页面中，
basically indexes into that physical page,
例如，如果偏移量是 12 ，
so, for example, the offset is, you know, 12.
那么你就知道
then you know there are
它使用的是
the 12th entry of that
那一页的第 12 个条目。
page is actually used.
很多人，
A lot of people a lot
很多人，你们中的很多人，
of you entered in the message
在回答这个问题时，
in the, in response to the question,
总是有一些方案，
there's always some scheme of taking
取一个偏移量，
an offset and adding that to
然后把它加到页面的底部，以获得实际的内存，
the base of the page to obtain the actual
物理内存位置，
memory, physical memory location, where
值存储或加载到那里。
a value store, where value will be loaded too.
关于 RISC-V 的
And one of the interesting things
一个有趣的事情是，
about the RISC-V is and
这是再次对
this is in response to some
一些问题的回答，
questions again,
有人问到物理地址
somebody asked look the physical
或虚拟地址都是 64 位。
or virtual addresses are 64 bits.
这完全正确，
Which makes totally sense correct,
因为 RISC-V 是
because the RISC-V is
64 位寄存器。
64-bit register.
但实际上
But in fact on the
在我们使用的
RISC-V processor, that we're using,
RISC-V 处理器上，
not all of the 64 bits
并不是使用了所有 64 位，
actually used,
也就是说，前 25 位
namely, the top 25 are
实际上根本没有使用。
actually not used at all.
这限制了
So that limits the
虚拟地址的大小，
size of a virtual address, that
这将虚拟地址空间的大小
limits the size of a virtual
限制为 2 的 39 次方，
address space 2 to the power of 39,
大约是 512 吉字节。
which is roughly 512 gigabytes.
当然，你知道
So, of course you
更高版本的处理器
know later version of the
可能支持更大的地址空间，
processor, might support bigger address spaces
这是必要的，
and that is necessary and could then
可以完成，例如，
be done, for example, some of those 25 bits
这 25 位没有使用，
that are basically unused, could be used to
可以用来构建更大的虚拟地址空间。
build bigger virtual address spaces.
在索引中，
So, and so in the index
你知道，剩下的 39 位
and, you know, where 39 bits left,
作为虚拟地址，
you know as the virtual address
其中 27 位是索引，
27, 27 bits are
我们一会儿就会看到，
index and we'll see you in
为什么
a second, why they are 27
27 位是索引，
are index and then
其他 12 位是偏移量。
the 12 are offset.
你知道，
And you know there has to
偏移量必须是 12 ，
be 12, because 2 to the
因为 2 的 12 次方是 4096 。
power 12 is 4096.
所以这是 RISC-V 的虚拟地址。
So that's virtual addresses on the
而物理地址
RISC-V. Physical addresses as you
正如你在看到的，
can see here are actually 56
实际上是 56 位宽。
bits wide.
所以物理内存，
So the physical memory,
可以大于
can be bigger than the
单个虚拟地址空间。
single virtual address space.
但它被限制在 2 的 56 次方，
But it's limited to 2 power to 56,
你知道，大多数主板可能
you know most boards probably, you know,
不支持 2 的 56 次方内存，
don't support 2 to the power
因为这是一个
of 56 physical memory, because
很大的物理内存。
a gigantic amount of physical memory.
但原则上这块板可以，
But in principle the
你知道，
board could, you know,
如果你能制造出
if you could manufacture it
2 的 56 次方的内存，
support two to the power
它也能支持。
of 56 physical memory.
因此，在该方案中，
And so in this scheme,
物理地址 56 位中，
then 56 bit for
44 位是物理页号，
the physical address, 44 are basically
即 PPM ，
the physical page number,
12 位是
the PPM, and 12 are the
直接从虚拟地址
offset that are inherited directly from
继承的偏移量。
the virtual address.
这能理解吗？
Does that make sense.
所以，在这里停一下。
So, um, you know stop for a second
你可以整理一下思绪，
here. So you collect your thoughts,
我想在这里指出的是，
the only point I wanted to
这个材料很重要，
make here is that this material is important,
所以可以问问题，
so just ask questions,
细节很重要，
the details matter,
它将是
and it will be a large
一大部分，
part of you,
你真的需要理解
you really need to understand all
所有这些东西，
this stuff,
才能做下一个实验，
to be able to basically
页表实验。
do lab, the next lab, the page table lab.
是的， Amiar ，说吧。
Yeah, Amiar, go ahead, please.
你能退一张幻灯片吗，
If you can go back
我的屏幕不清楚。
one slide, I have the screen is unclear.
哪一页，
Which one,
页表这张吗？是的。
the page table slide? Yeah.
这张吗？嗯，不是。
This one? Um, no.
最新的那一张，
The most recent one, but it
但也不要紧，
also doesn't really matter,
是的，就是这张，
yeah, this is perfect,
谢谢你，所以我想知道的是
thank you, so I'm wondering this
这个叫做页的 4096 字节的范围，
4096 byte range which we've called
是作为内存中的
a page, is that assigned as
连续区块分配的吗？
a continuous chunk in memory.
是的，这是
Yes, that's a continuous physical,
物理内存中
continuous range of 4096 bytes
连续的的 4096 字节。
including memory.
我明白了，然后。你知道，
I see, and then. You know, the map,
映射是以 4096 字节作为粒度。
granularity of 4096 bytes.
好的，然后是偏移量 12 ，
Okay, and then 12, the
2 的 12 次方是 4096 ，
offset, like 2 to the 12 is 4096,
那么这足以
so that's sufficient to cover each
覆盖每一块？是的，页面中的每个字节。
of the chunks? Yeah, each byte in the page.
在这个图表中，
And where does the 56 come
数字 56 是从哪里来的，
from, in the diagram, I could
这之前我一直可以理解，
follow up until then,
但我不知道
but I didn't get where
它是从哪里来的。
that came from.
这是设计师们决定的的。
The designers cook it up.
硬件设计师决定
So the hardware designers decide
物理地址有多大，
how big you know physical
对于他们想要
addresses, basically for whatever board
设计的任何电路板，
they want to design,
所以 RISC-V 设计师
and so the RISC-V
决定使用 56 ，
designers who decided at 56,
觉得选择这个物理地址
that physical addresses were a
是一个好主意。
good idea.
通常，他们得出
And usually the way they
这些数字的方式
come up with these numbers is
是看技术趋势。
they look at technology trends.
然后说，我们
And say like, well, we want
希望电路板
to be able for the next
在接下来的 5 年里适用，
sort of 5 years,
你知道，他们预测
you know, we don't predict the physical
物理内存不会
memory will be ever bigger than
大于 2 的 56 次方。
2 to the power 56.
也许他们认为它
Probably they think it won't be
不会比小于 2^56 的东西更大，
bigger than something much smaller,
但你知道，
but then you know give them
留一些余量，
sort of leeway, you know,
为了防止他们的预测是错误的，
in case you know their predictions wrong,
他们会选择一个稍微大一点的数字。
they pick a slightly bigger number.
这个能理解吗？
Is that makes sense.
好的，谢谢。是的，很多人
Yeah, thanks. Yeah, a lot of people
问起这个。
ask about this.
还有其他人吗，谁举手了，
Anybody else, who raised a hand,
我想
I think there's a bunch of
有很多人在提问，
people asking questions and unfortunately my
不过，我的 zoom
zoom doesn't show its more than
在有多个人举手的时候，
two people raised hands just multiple
不会显示超过两个人。
people are raising their hands.
所以如果你有问题，
So you please jump in, if
请直接说吧。
you have a question.
好的。我有一个问题，
Okay. I have a question,
是的，说吧。如果虚拟内存
yeah, go ahead. So if the virtual
是 2 的 27 次方，
memory is up to 2 to the power of 27
而物理内存
and the physical memory is
是 2 的 56 次方，
up 2 to the power of 56, right,
那么，我们可以
so, we could have,
有多个进程，
like we could have multiple processes
这些进程可以耗尽
that could exhaust all their virtual
所有的虚拟内存，
memories without
而不会用完所有的物理内存，
using up all the physical memory,
对吗？是的，没错。
right? That's correct.
这是完全正确的。
That's absolutely correct.
好的。我也有个问题。
Okay. I have a question, too.
好的，说吧。
Yeah, go ahead.
所以这个物理地址
So this 56 for the physical
的 56 是可能的
address is that the,
n内存位置的数目。
the number of possible memory locations.
我认为这不是位的数目，
I don't think it's the
因为处理器是 64 位的机器。
number of bits because the 64 bit machine.
56 可以扩大到 64 ，
That 56 could go up to 64,
但是他们选择只使用 56 位。
but they just choose it to have just 56.
没错，
That's correct,
从一种角度来看，
one way to think about it,
他们在板上只使用 56 位，
then they only have to run
而不是 64 位。
56 wide on the board as opposed to 64.
我明白了。
I see, I see.
好吧。我也有一个问题，
Okay. I also have a question,
你能
um, so kind of, could you
倒退一张幻灯片吗。好的。
go back one slide maybe. Yeah.
从 CPU 开始，
so from the CPU,
我们通过 MMU ，
we go through the MMU and
然后再到内存，
then to the memory, but
但是不同进程的
where, where here is the distinction
区别在哪里，
for different processes, because like each
因为每个进程，
process, like process, like the shell
比如 shell 进程有地址 0x1000 ，
process has something at address like 0x1000,
然后 ls 进程
and then the ls process
也有地址 0x1000 ，
also has something at address 0x1000, so
所以我们需要将它们
we need to translate those to
转换成不同的物理地址，所以。是的，
different physical, so. Yeah, the satp register,
通过 satp 寄存器，这个寄存器包含
contains, the register who contains the
要使用的映射的地址。
address of which map to use.
所以 ls 使用自己的映射，
So ls runs with its own map,
cat 也使用自己的映射。
you know cat with its own map.
好的，所以是每个进程
OK, so each process will have
都有自己的映射。是的。
its completely own map. Yeah.
理解了，谢谢。
Makes sense, thank you.
事实上，有一个很好的方法
In fact, there's a great a
到达下一个知识点，
way to the next,
所以如果每个进程都有自己的映射。
point, so if every process has its own map.
这个映射有多大，
You know how big is this
就像我在这里画的那样。
map, like that I've drawn here.
是的，这张图里是
Well, that map is 2 to
2 的 27 次方，
the power 27 entries, correct,
那可是相当大的一个数。
and that's pretty big.
如果每个进程
And I would fill physical
都完全填充映射，
memory reasonable quickly,
物理内存将会
if every process exactly how
很快用完。
to complete you know populated map.
然后是巨大的，
And then there's gigantic, means that
意味着每个进程都非常大，
every process is very big,
所以实际上
and so in fact this is
硬件不是这样
not the way hardware actually
存储页表的，
stores page tables,
你可以把它想成
you can think about it
一个数组，
conceptually as an array,
从 0 到 2 的 27 次方，
you know going from zero to 2 power 27,
但实际上并不是这样的。
but actually is not what happens in practice.
实际上，
In practice,
这是一个多级结构，
it's a multi-level structure that
这才是真正的 RISC-V 页表。
here's actually the real RISC-V page table.
页表结构以及硬件实现。
Structure and what the hardware implements.
我们之前知道的
And so what happens with the
作为索引的开始的 27 位会发生什么变化。
27 bits that we started earlier, the index.
它实际上被分成
It's actually split in three
三个 9 位数字。
9 bit numbers.
最前面的九位
And the first, the top nine
用于索引
bits, are used to index into
顶层页表，
the top level page table,
也就是他们所称的目录。
directory as they are called.
然后一个目录，
And so, then one directory,
它们中的一个，
you know one of these guys,
大小是 4096 字节，
you know is 4096 bytes, 4096 bytes,
就像页面大小一样。
just like the page size.
一个 PTE 条目，
A PTE entry, one of
其中的一个条目是 64 字节，
the entries in the thing is 64 bytes,
不好意思，我的意思是 64 位，，就像寄存器一样，
64 bit, I mean, sorry, like the register
有 8 个字节。
with so eight bytes.
所以这就意味着
And so there's going to mean
使用 4096 处以 8 ，
that you do 4096
表示
divided by eight, means there are
其中一个目录页中
512 entries in one of those
有 512 个条目。
directory pages.
因此，基本上情况是，
So basically what happens is
satp 寄存器指向
like the satp points to the top
顶层根目录，
root directory,
我们将顶层的 9 位索引
we take the top level 9
放入页目录中。
bits index into the page directory.
现在给了我们
And now gives us a new
一个新的物理页码。
physical page number.
这个物理页码是
And that physical page number
下一级页面目录的地址，
is the page directory for the next level,
所以当我们使用
so when we use the
下一级索引，
next level index,
来索引到
to index into that page
该页面目录，
directory and then you know
然后继续，
and so forth,
我们想要找到一个，
you know, we'd like to find
我们想得到
one we get the bottom level
最低级别的页面目录。
page directory.
它为我们提供了条目，
And that basically gives us the entry,
将虚拟地址映射到
that maps the virtual address
物理地址。
to physical address.
在某种意义上，
So in some sense,
它与我在上一张幻灯片中展示的
it's very similar to where I
非常相似，
showed in the previous slide except
除了索引发生在三个步骤
they're basically the index happens in
而不是一个步骤中。
three steps instead of one step.
这就是优点，
And this is advantage,
这种方案的主要优点是
the main advantage of this scheme
大部分地址空间
is that large parts of the
没有被使用，
address space are not being used,
你不需要为
you don't have to have any
没有使用的地址空间创建页表条目。
page table entries for that.
例如，
For example,
假设你有一个
let's say you have a new
新的地址空间。
address space.
它只有一页，
That has only one page like
比如最下面的一页。
the bottom page.
是的，4096 。
Yeah, 4096.
并且没有其他页面
And no other pages in
在地址空间中，
the address space,
因此实际只映射地址
so only addresses 0 to 4095(6)
0 到 4095(6) 。
are actually mapped.
你需要多少个页表条目
How many page table entry or
或页表目录
page table directories you need
来映射这个特殊的页。
to map that particular page.
嗯，你需要一个顶层的。
Well, you need one of the top, correct.
你需要该条目中的
And you need basically value in
值为 0 ，
that entry for zero,
最高级别的 9 位，
the top level 9 bits,
你知道 0 ，
you know zero, zero so you
所以你需要一个 0 的条目。
need an entry for 0.
然后你需要
So that means you need one
一个中级条目，
middle level entry,
你知道它对应于
you know that basically corresponds
下一个，
to the next,
你知道九个 0 比特，
you know nine 0 bits and
然后一个条目对应接下来的
then one entry for the next
九个 0 比特。
nine zero bits.
所以我们只需要
So basically we get away with
三个页目录就可以了。
three page directories.
在我们上一张幻灯片的
In our previous scheme on the
方案中，
previous slide correct,
我们有 2 的 27 次方个条目，
we have 2 to the power
现在我们
27 entries and now we basically
只需要有 3 乘以 512 个
have to have 3 times whatever
条目就可以了。
512 entries that we're done.
这就是
That's the main reason why
实际硬件
you know the actual hardware
使用多级树方案的
has this hierarchical,
主要原因。
multi-level tree scheme.
有人要提问吗，
Any questions about this, because it's
因为这很重要。
pretty important.
Samir ，说吧。
Samir, go ahead.
我的问题是，
So my question is as since
每个页表的 PPN 号
the PPM number from each page
是 44 位。
table is 44 bits.
第二个，比如
And the second say the middle
虚拟内存中间的表。
table resides on the virtual memory.
我们从哪里得到丢失的 12 位。
Where do we get the missing 12 bits from.
最后 12 位，
Well, the final twelve bits okay
好的，
so good good good,
所以你说的是这 44 位，对吗。
so you're saying these 44, correct.
是的。这是怎么回事，
Yes. What is going on with that,
所有的页面目录或
while all page, all page directories
页面行，
or page line,
它们是
and so they basically they're a
44 位物理页码
physical page number is 44 plus
加上 12 个零位。
twelve, twelve zero bits.
如果我们看
And so what actually happens if
这些PTE条目，
we look at these PTE entries,
它们都有相同的形式，
they all have the same sort of form,
如果你看这中的一个。
if you look at one of these guys.
有 44 位，
There are 44 bits,
还有 12 位是 0 ，
there are 12 bits 0,
所以我们得到了
so that gives us a
44 加 12 是 56 ，
44 plus 12 is 56, so
这是一个物理地址，
that gives us a physical address,
这意味着 64 位中，
and so that means there's 64 bits,
实际上还有一些位
there's actually some bits left
没有使用，
there not being used and
事实上，
in fact the bottom 12
最下面的 12 位，
bits were basically or the
或者说最下面的 10 位，
bottom 10 definitely bottom based
完全没有使用，
on not used at all, and
事实上，页面硬件
in fact the paging hardware
存储了一系列
stores or stores a bunch
控制转换的标志，
of flags that control the
我们很快会
translation and we'll talk about
讨论这些标志。
those flags in the second.
用它们来
And with their
控制转换，
to control the translation and
它们存储在
they're stored basically in the bottom
最下面的10位。
10 bits.
这也意味着，
It also means that, you
这两个加起来
know, if you add these two
就是 54 位，
up that's 54 bits,
还剩下 10 位
basically there's 10 bits left.
没有使用，这 10 位
There are unused, those 10 bits
也是
are again,
为了将来的增长（保留的），
you know for future growth,
所以在某个时候，
so at some point we might
我们可能会有
have a new type of
一种新型的 RISC-V 处理器，
RISC-V processor, that will have a
它的页表结构会略有不同，
slightly different structure page tables,
它实际上可能会
and it might actually have bigger
有比 44 位更大的
than 44 bits for the physical
物理页码。理解了吗？谢谢。
page number. OK? Thank you.
事实上，
In fact you can see
你可以在这里看到，
it here like if you
如果你看一下
look at a single entry
这里画的单个条目，
direct that's drawn here,
你知道它们还
you know they're basically.
剩下 10 位，
10, 10 bits left, that
未被使用。
are not being used.
好的，我们来看一下
Okay, so let's look at the flags
这些标志位，
for a second, because it's sort
因为它们很重要。
of important.
那么，每个转换条目的最后 10 位，
so, every translation in the bottom 10
都存储了一系列标志位，
bits, there's a bunch of flag
第一个标志位是 valid 。
stored and the first flag is valid.
如果设置了有效位，
If a valid bit set,
则意味着这是有效 PTE ，
that means this is a valid PTE,
你可以用它来转换。
and you can use it for translation.
因此，我们
And so, we're going to
这里使用的例子，
run my little example, that I
三个页面目录，
used here, three page directories,
当只使用条目 0 时，
when only entry 0 is used
只有条目 0 设置
then only entey 0 will have
有效位，
valid bit set and none of
其他 511 个条目
the other 511 entries
都不会设置有效位。
will not have valid bit set.
这告诉 MMU ，
And that basically tells MMU,
你不需要追查这个 PTE ，
well, you don't have to chase
这个 PTE
down this PTE, PTE just contains no
不包含有效信息。
valid information.
然后 R 表示允许
Then "R" means you're allowed
从该页读取，
to read from that page, write
write 表示允许向该页写入。
means you're allowed to write to the page.
Execute 表示允许
Execute means you're allowed to execute
执行其中的指令。
instruction from it.
User 表示本页
User, means you know this page is
可以被在用户空间中
also accessible by a process
运行的进程访问。
running in user space.
然后，其他的位
And then the other bits you
不那么重要，
not that important,
它会在某个时候出现，
it will show up at
这是五个比较重要的
some point, those are sort of five
标志位。
important bits.
理解了吗？
Does that make sense.
是的， Nithya ，我可能会念错你的名字，
Yeah, Nithya, I'd probably mispronouncing your
我向你道歉。
name I apologize to you.
就是这样读的，
That's, that's the representation,
谢谢，
thank you,
我有一个关于
I had a quick question about,
三个页表的问题，
the three page table,
那么地址或
so how are the addresses or
PPN 值是如何组合在一起
like the PPN values combined to form
形成最终物理地址的，
the final physical address, I might
我可能错过了这个。
miss that.
嗯，是的，
Um, yeah,
我可能说得
I may not say that said it
不是很清楚。
very explicitly. So the first
因此，第一个 PPN 位于页表的顶部，
PPN correcting tops the page table,
即顶级页面目录中的
the first PPN in the top
第一个 PPN 。
level page directory.
它包含下一级
And contains the physical address of
的物理地址。
the next level down.
这个页目录
And one contains the one next
又包含下一级，
level down and then in the
在最后一级仍然包含 44 位，
final one we still have are
它包含了
[] 44 bits that contains then
我们实际上
the actual physical address off the
需要转换的页面的
page that we're actually trying to
物理地址。
translate to.
好的，理解了，谢谢。
OK, that makes sense, thank you.
好的，还有一个有趣的问题，
Okay, and one interesting question,
让我们先说一下，
just let us side note,
在回答其他两个问题之前，
before let me answer my
我先回答一下
own question before answering the
自己的问题，
two raised hands here,
回顾这张图片，
look back at this picture,
为什么是物理页码
why, why are the physical page
存储在这些页面目录中。
numbers stored in these page directories.
为什么不是虚拟地址？
Why not a virtual address.
因为我们需要
Because we need to look it
在内存中查找它，比如
up in memory, like look up
在内存中查找下一个目录。
the next directory in memory.
是的，
Yeah right,
我们不能让
we could not have a
一种转换方式
translation scheme depends on yet
依赖另一种转换方式，
another translation scheme,
你知道我们可以
you know we could sort of,
递归查找，
recursive intent look, so that
所以这里解释一下。
just make sense.
这就是正确的答案，
That's exactly the right answer,
它必须是一个物理地址数，
it has to be a physical number,
那么 satp 寄存器呢，
how about the satp,
你怎么使用 satp 寄存器，
what do you use the satp,
它存储什么，
what does it store it store
存储的是物理地址还是虚拟地址？
a physical address or a virtual address.
也是物理的，
Also physical, assuming that
第一页目录也是在内存中。
the first page directory is
完全正确，
also memory, right. Exactly so
所以它必须是
it has to be a
一个物理地址数，因为我们实际上
physical number because we're actually
是用它来转换。
trying to use it for translation.
而且，你知道 satp 寄存器，
And, so you know the satp, you
你需要知道
need to know what the physical
路由到
page number is,
页面目录的
on the route of the
物理页码是什么。
page directory.
好的，还有两个问题，
OK, there were two other questions
两个人举手，
or two people who raise their
你可以，
hands, you do,
重复你的问题，如果。
repeat your question if.
这里有一个
So there's a hierarchy of three
由三个表组成的层次结构，
tables and each of them is
每个表都由虚拟地址的
indexed by a part of the
一部分进行索引，
virtual address,
每个索引是 9 位。
each 9 bits long.
我不确定
So I'm not sure
我是否理解它们之间的链接
I understand how chaining between
是如何发生的，
them happens and what it's
以及它意味着什么，比如，
meant to accomplish, like shouldn't
仅仅使用
it be sufficient to just
这三个 9 位地址
use those three 9 bit
来索引它们中的每一个
addresses to index into each
难道不够吗？
of them.
没错，
That's correct,
所以第一个
so the first, top level
顶层 9 位用来
9 bits are used to
在页顶层目录
index the first
中索引，
top, page top directory,
第二个在下一个中进行索引，
the second and the next
第三个在第三个目录中。
one and the third in the third one.
因此，可能我没有正确
So maybe I'm just not understanding
理解这一点，
this correctly,
所以当一个进程
so when a process requests
请求查找
a certain virtual address to be
某个虚拟地址时，
looked up,
它会加载到
it loads into the
satp 寄存器，
satp register or the CPU
CPU 会
does and that,
得到相应的
get to the corresponding correct highest
最高级别页表。
level page table.
然后是那个页表，将。
And then that page table will.
我们使用了
We used in the top
27 位中的开头的 9 位
level 9 bits from the 27
来索引该页目录。
to index into that page directory.
然后结果是什么呢，
And then what is what is
结果是，
the result of that,
比如什么都没有，
like if the result is there's
MMU 会创建
nothing there does MMU
一个页面表吗？
create a page table,
不，
No, no,
MMU 基本上会告诉
MMU basically tells the operating
操作系统或处理器，
system or tells the processor,
很抱歉我无法转换该地址，
sorry I couldn't translate that address,
会导致页面错误，
and basically turns into a
我们稍后
page fault which we'll talk about
会讨论这个问题。
a little bit later.
但是不能转换地址，
But just cannot translate the address,
它不能转换，
it doesn't translate it's like you
就像你知道被零除，
know you can't divide by zero,
你知道如果你试图
you know if you try to
这样做，处理器会
do that, the processor refuses to
拒绝这样做。
do it.
我明白了，好的。
I see, OK.
Brandon ，你呢。
Brandon, what about you, Brandon.
我只是想
So I just wanted to
确保我理解是正确的，
make sure I understand, how I
也许想知道
think maybe we want to understand
中间页表是怎么，
how the intermediate page tables well,
怎么计算它们的物理地址的。
how we calculate the physical address of those.
那么，这个是否正确，
So, is it correct that say if
如果我们试图找到
we're trying to find a second
第二级页表的物理地址，
level page tables physical address,
我们将从第一级页表中
we would take the PPN from
拿到 PPN ，
the first level page table,
即 44 位，
that's 44 bits and then we
然后我们将原始虚拟地址
add the 12 bit offset from
的 12 位偏移量相加，
the original virtual address to get
以获得完整的 56 位，就是这个问题。
the full 56 bit, this question is.
我们不需要将
We don't add the offset
虚拟地址的偏移量相加，
from the virtual address,
我们只取 12 个零位。
we just take twelve 0 bits.
所以我们取 PPN ，
So we take the PPN
有 44 位。好的。
there's 44 bits. Okay,
底部有 12 个零位，
12 0 bits on the bottom
这给了我们一个
and that gives us a
56 位的物理地址，
56 bit physical address and
这就是下一页目录的位置，
that's where the next page directories,
这要求每个页目录的页
and this requires that basically every
都是对齐的。
page directories page aligned.
我明白了，好的，我理解了。
I see, OK, that makes sense.
这些都是很棒的问题，
So these are all great questions
这些都是
and these are all things,
你们会在 page table 实验
you're gonna be struggling within the
中用到的。
page table lab so.
现在提问是
Yeah it's very good to ask
非常好的。
them right now.
好的，让我想想，
Okay, let me see,
好的，
Yes, yeah okay,
让我稍等一下。
let me hold on for a second.
我整理一下思绪，
And I quote my thoughts
看看到哪里了。
see where I am.
好的，
Good good,
good, okay,
一种，
one a sort of you
还有一件事
know one other thing that I
我想提一下，
want to mention because you will
因为你会看到，
see that, is that if
如果我们想一想，
we think about this,
你知道我刚才
you know the scheme that I
展示的方案，
just showed right,
看起来发生的是
what really seems to be
我们将值
going on is that we load
加载或存储到内存中。
or store value to memory.
在处理器加载或存储值
What the processor loads or stores
到内存中，
value to memory,
我们必须查找
we basically have to do free
空闲内存，对吧，
memory lookups, right,
一个在页面目录
one in the top of the
的顶部，
page directory,
一个在中间页面目录，
one intermediate page
然后
directory and then one in the
一个在最底层的页面目录。
bottom level page directory.
看起来，
It looks like, that you know
任何对虚拟地址的内存引用
any memory reference to virtual address
都需要访问空闲内存。
basically requires free memory reach.
这是很昂贵的。
And so that seems expensive.
那么，
And so,
实际上，
what happens in practice where
在几乎所有处理器都这样做的，
almost all every processor does this,
它的有一个缓存，
it has a cache sitting
其中包含
on the side, that contains
最近使用的转换。
recently used translations.
这被称为转换后备缓冲器。
And this is called translation look-aside buffer.
你会经常看到
Then you'll see that term
这个术语， TLB 。
quite often, of TLB.
基本上，
Basically it's nothing else than
它只是
the cache of
页表条目、 PTE 条目的缓存。
entry, page table entries, PTE entries.
因此，当进程
So when the process has you
进程路由第一次
know the first time the process
查找虚拟地址时，
routes look through virtual address,
你知道，
you know walks this, hardware
硬件遍历此页，
walks this page, the three
即三级页面表，
level page tables, that will come
会得到最终物理页，
out with you know the final
叫做那个特定虚拟地址的
physical page, often called final PPN,
最终 PPN ，
for that particular virtual address,
然后 TLB
and then basically the
存储了 VA PA PN
TLB stores, VA, PA, PN,
或 PA 映射。
or PA mapping on the side.
因此，
And so,
下一次查找那个
then the next time you refer
特定的虚拟地址时，
to that particular virtual address,
我只需直接
I can just look at straight
访问 TLB ，
up in the TLB and the
TLB 就会做出响应，
TLB will respond instead of having
而不必执行页表遍历。
to do the page table walk.
是的， Amiar 。
Yep, Amiar.
因此， TLB 将
So, the TLB map
虚拟地址映射到
virtual addresses to the physical address
页面的物理地址，
of the page, that the virtual
虚拟地址和偏移量
address along with the offset
一起，
absolutely,
那么在页表级别
wouldn't it be more efficient
进行缓存
to like cache at the
不是更有效吗？
page table level.
好的，
Okay, so I let me
让我退一步，
take a step back here,
实现 TLB 有
there are many ways of
很多种方式，
implementing the TLB,
最重要的是，
the most important thing that
你需要知道
you need to know is that
有一个 TLB 。
there is a TLB.
至于 TLB 具体
And the exact details
是怎么实现的，
of actually how the TLB
你知道，
has implemented, this sort of
这个话题
you know not a topic
我们不会
that we're going to talk
讲太多细节。
about in great amount of detail.
那根本不是，
That's not at all,
所以这实际上
and so this is really
是位于处理器内部的东西，
something that sits inside of the
大部分对操作系统
processor and is mostly hidden from
是隐藏的，
the operating system,
操作系统并不知道
the operating system doesn't really know
TLB 是如何操作的，
how to TLB be operates, the
你需要知道 TLB 存在
only thing the reason you need
的唯一原因是，
to know that the TLB
如果你切换页表，
exist is that if you switch page tables,
然后，通常操作系统需要
then, typically the operating system needs
告诉处理器
to tell the processor that's switching
正在切换页表。
page tables.
并且需要刷新TLB。
And the TLB needs to be flushed.
因为如果发送的是
Because basically you send
旧的条目，
stale entries,
但是如果你切换到
but if you switch to a
新的页表，
new page table,
TLB 中的条目
the entries in the TLB may
可能不再有效，
not be valid anymore and so
因此需要删除它们，
they need to be removed because
否则转换将是
otherwise you know the translation would
不正确的。
be incorrect.
所以操作系统
And so the operating system is
通常
typically aware
会知道
it's aware that there's a,
有一个 TLB ，
that there is a TLB
只是偶尔
only basically to tell the
告诉硬件，
hardware once in a while saying,
好的，我们不再使用它们了，
okay we'll don't use them anymore,
因为我要交换页表。
because I'm gonna switch page tables.
事实上，
And in fact on you know
在 RISC-V 上，
the, the RISC-V, the instruction
刷新 TLB 的指令是 sfence_vma。
to flush the TLB is called sfence_vma.
我不是很确定，
I'm not actually,
刷新 TLB 。[Biback] 。
flush the TLB. [Biback].
所以我有一个问题，
So I have a question,
不是关于 TLB ，
like not regarding TLB
而是带来了
but that brought kind
这个问题。
of this question.
三级支持，
The three level support, that the
我们拥有的三级分页，
three level paging that we have,
是由操作系统还是
is it implemented by the operating
硬件本身实现的？
system or the hardware itself. It
它是在硬件中实现的。
implemented in hardware.
你知道所有这些
So you know there's all happens
都发生在硬件上，
in hardware,
MMU 是硬件的一部分。
the MMU is a block of hardware.
在操作系统中，
In the operating system we'll
我们很快
see in a second when we
就会看到 xv6 ，
look at xv6, xv6
xv6 有一个模拟
has a function that models the
页表遍历的函数，
page table walk, because once in
因为有时 xv6
a while you know xv6
必须做硬件
basically has to do what the
所做的事情。
hardware does.
所以它有一个
And so it knows
叫 walk 的函数，
it does have a function
基本上
called walk, that basically does
做的是完全一样的事情，
exactly the same thing,
但是是在软件中。
but in software.
那么，我能问个问题吗？
So, can I ask a question?
那么，在此方案中，
So, where in this scheme does the
处理器缓存适合的位置，
processor cache fit,
是在地址转换之前
does it happen before the address
还是之后，
translation or after,
因为。好的，
because. Yeah, okay let me so
让我们往后调几个，
let's switch back a little bit
让我找一下。
a couple, let me see.
好的，通常 MMU ，
Okay, usually MMU will
思考的方式是
really the way to think about
所有这些东西，
is that all this stuff,
整个部分
you know the whole block is
都在处理器里。
inside the processor silicon.
所以这里有一个
So there's a RISC-V
RISC-V 芯片，
chip and inside of it
它的内部是 CPU ，
is the CPU,
实际上有多个 CPU ，
in fact there are multiple CPU
有 4 个内核。
correct, there 4 cores.
这是一个 MMU ，
And there's a MMU
你可以想一想，
and you know you can think about that,
在 CPU 这一边，
either on this on the CPU side,
有一个 TLB 。
you know there's a TLB.
这个理解了，
That makes sense,
但我想
but I guess my question
我的问题是关于，
was about the like,
缓存不只是 TLB ，
cache in terms of not the TLB,
而是一个普通的缓存，
but just a normal cache like,
比如，有时我们实际上
sometimes we don't actually go all
不会一直访问内存。
the way to access the memory.
好的，不错的想法。
Yeah, good points I think I
我想我应该在上周的周一，
should like to scheme last week
RISC-V 处理器
correctly, on monday of the RISC-V
有一个缓存，
processor and has one cache
有两个缓存。
it has two cache.
有些缓存使用物理地址索引，
Some caches are indexed by physical
有些缓存使用
address, some caches are indexed by
虚拟地址索引。
virtual address.
因此，按虚拟地址索引的缓存
So the caches that are indexed
位于 MMU 之前。
by virtual address sit before the MMU.
按物理地址索引缓存
And cache in their index by
位于 MMU 之后。
physical addresses after the MMU.
这个可以理解吗？
Does that make sense?
我也有一个问题，
Can I also ask a question
我的问题是，
my question is,
你说 TLB ，
you said that the TLB,
它遍历，所以我把东西
it walks so I like to
放进 TLB ，
put stuff into TLB,
硬件遍历页表。
the hardware walks through the page tables.
如果硬件可以做到这一点，
Why do we arrive walk function,
我们为什么要实现遍历功能。
if hardware can do that.
很好的问题，
Very good question,
一个原因是，
one reason we have, a
其实有几个原因，
couple of reasons why we do
或者为什么 xv6 需要它，
it or why xv6 needs it,
一个是它实际
one is when it actually sets
设置初始页表的时候。
up the initial page tables.
你知道它需要
you know it needs to
对三级页表进行编程。
program the the three levels.
所以它需要
And so it needs to basically
模仿这三个层级。
emulate the three levels.
嗯，还有另一个例子，
Um, and um, another example,
在 syscall 实验中
that you actually sort of run
遇到或
into or are running into in
正在遇到的是，
the syscall lab is that when
当你复制， xv6 ，
you copy, the xv6, the
或者说内核有自己的页表，
kernel has its own page table
每个用户地址空间
and every user address space has
都有自己的页表。
its own page table.
偶尔，
And once in a while,
例如，有些信息
for example it says [info], you know, like
指向系统基础设施，
system, pointed to system infrastructure,
它运行在用户空间。
you know that lives in user space.
内核需要
The kernel needs to translate
将其转换为
to an address that it can
可以用来读写的地址。
use to read and write.
所以，
And so,
举个例子，如果你看
for example if you're looking
copyin 和 copyout 。
copyin or copyout.
基本上，内核使用
Basically, the kernel translates the
用户页表来转换
user virtual address using the user
用户虚拟地址，
virtual, using a user page
获取物理地址，
table to get out of physical
然后内核
address, that kernel
获得一个地址，
then get an address out,
内核可以使用该地址
actually the kernel can use to
来读写该内存。
read and write that memory.
有好几个地方
So there's a bunch of places
会出现这种情况，
going to show up, and I'll
我希望在 10 分钟或
talk about hopefully in whatever ten
15 分钟内谈到。
minutes or fifteen minutes.
我有一个问题，
I have a question,
为什么硬件不
why doesn't the hardware like expose
公开遍历函数，
that walk function,
这样我们就不必
so we don't have to write
编写自己的函数，而且里面
our own and potentially have bugs
可能有 bug ，
in it,
为什么不像这样，
why isn't there like, maybe
也许有一个特权指令，
a privileged instruction that you can
你可以传递一个虚拟地址，
pass a virtual address and will
然后返回物理地址。
give back the physical address.
好的，这就像
Well, this is just like just
是存储到虚拟地址，
store to the virtual address
你又绕回来了，
you get back and will do
硬件会为你做好，
it right for you,
所以我稍后会看到，
so I will see later on,
在下一个实验中，
in the next lab,
page table 实验，
the page table lab,
实际上就是
in fact is exactly what you'll
你要做的事情，
be doing you'll actually set up
你会以稍微不同的方式设置页表，
the page table slightly differently,
这样你就可以避免
so that you can avoid the
在 copyin 和 copyinstr 中遍历。
walk in copyin and copyinstr.
我想这一点
I think this will become clear
在我们讨论查看 xv6 的时候
in the second we when we
就会变得清晰起来，好吗。
talk about we look at the xv6, OK.
好的。
Okay, good.
在跳到 xv6 之前，
One more sure basically before jumping
我想说明一点。
into xv6, I wanted to make one point.
说明一种考虑页表的方式。
One way to think about, you know, page tables.
一种流行的说法。
A popular way to phrase this.
页表提供了
It's the page tables provide
一定程度的间接性。
a level of indirection.
基本上
And, that and, so basically
这种间接性，
this indirection,
就是
what I'm talking about you know
之前讨论的从虚拟地址到
this mapping from virtual address to
物理地址的映射。
physical address.
并且该映射完全
And this mapping is completely
在操作系统的控制之下。
under control of the operating system.
正如我们已经看到的，
As we've seen, you know in the last
在最后几张幻灯片中我们谈到的，
a couple slides that we talk,
这意味着
and that means that the
操作系统因为它
operating system because it has so
有这么多的控制权，
much control,
它有完全的控制权，
it has control complete control that
控制转换，
translation, it can do all
它可以做各种有意思的技巧。
kinds of interesting tricks.
举个例子，
And so for example, like
有一个技巧，
one trick, talk a little
稍微谈谈这个，
bit about this,
比如如果一个
like if a page, page entry is
页面条目是无效的，
invalid and will really return a
你知道硬件
page you know the hardware will
会抛出页面错误。
raise page fault.
作为对页面错误的响应，
In response the page fault,
操作系统
the operating system could update
可以更新页表，
the page tables and then
然后重新启动该指令。
maybe restart the instruction.
因此，
And so there are all kinds
在运行时，
of things they can do, at
通过操作页表，
runtime, and by manipulating
可以做各种各样的事情。
the page tables.
我们今天不会
And we're not going to talk
讨论这个话题，
about it today,
但是两周后，
but in two weeks,
我们有一节课来
we'll have a lecture exactly about
讨论这个话题，一旦你有了
this topic about what cool things
页表和页面错误，
can you do, once you have
你可以做什么很酷的事情。
page tables and page faults.
但重要的是
But it's important to keep
要记住，这是一种
in mind that this is
令人难以置信的强大机制。
incredibly powerful mechanism.
那会给操作系统
That, will provide the operating system
带来极大的灵活性。
with a tremendous amount of flexibility.
这也是页表
And there's one reason why page
如此受欢迎的原因之一。
tables are so popular.
好的，我接下来
Okay, so what I wanna do
要做的是讨论 xv6 。
next is actually talk about xv6.
看看在 xv6 中
Sort of see how
这些是怎么发生的。
it all plays out in xv6.
所以我要做的第一件事，
So the first thing I'm gonna
是看看
do, is going to look
内核页面布局，
at the kernel page layout,
如果你愿意的话，
if you will, and
整个映射在这张幻灯片上，
the mapping is on this slide,
这是内核的
so here's the
虚拟地址空间，
virtual address space of the kernel,
这是物理内存，
here is, actually the physical memory,
所以这就是你
so this is basically whatever you
想到的东西，是 DRAM 。
can think about this is DRAM.
然而事实上并非如此，
And in fact it is not,
让我收回来一点，
let me take that back immediately
其中一个部分是 DRAM 。
one part is DRAM.
还有一部分实际上是 IO 设备。
And one part is actually IO devices.
也许我会
And so, to sort of maybe, I'm
先谈一下
going to talk about the physical,
幻灯片的右边，
the right side of the slide a
然后我们再谈
little bit first, and then we'll
幻灯片的左边。
talk about the left side in a second.
因此，
So the left side of
幻灯片的左侧完全由硬件决定。
the slide is completely determined by the hardware.
所以硬件设计师
And so the hardware designers
决定了合适的布局，
basically determined the layout of that
就像你上周看到的那样。
fit and you know as you saw before last week.
当内核启动时，它从地址 0x8000 开始。
When the kernel starts, it starts at this address 0x8000.
这是由硬件设计师决定的。
And that's determined by the hardware designers.
所以你应该更清楚，
And so you should be more explicit,
如果你查看电路板，
if you look at the board,
这是我周一展示的同一张电路板的图片，
this is the same picture of the board, that I showed on
但是一张更好的图片，
Monday but is hopefully a little better picture,
很容易看到，
it's easy to see,
这是我们的 RISC-V 处理器。
here's our RISC-V processor.
我们知道 RISC-V 处理器有四个内核，
And we now know correct in the RISC-V processor,
也有 MMU 。
there four cores, but there's also, MMU.
还有一个 TLB 或多个 TLB ，
And there's also a TLB or
每个内核都有自己的 MMU ，
multiple TLB, every core has its own MMU and every
每个内核都有自己的 TLB 。
core has its own TLB.
这是 DRAM 芯片。
And here are DRAM chips.
所以由电路板的设计者
And so basically the designers of
决定，
the board have decided that,
你知道，
when, you know, after, you
在从虚拟地址到
know, the translation from virtual to
物理地址的转换之后，
physical address basic physical addresses that's
基本物理地址从 08 开始，
starting you know at 08,
DRAM 芯片很多地方置零。
you know, a lot of zeros actually go to the DRAM chips.
0x8 以下的地址
Addresses above below 0x8, may go
可能是不同的 IO 设备。
to different IO devices.
所以平台决定，
And so the platform decides
设计者来决定，
basically the designers this board have
这块板的物理布局。
decided exactly what the physical layout.
我想你可以查一下物理布局，
I think you can look that up the physical layout,
如果你想看，让我给你看看，
if you want to, just let me show you so here's
这是我在星期一
the same manual that I showed
给你们看的同一本手册，
you on, um,
如果你转到第 31 页，
on um, Monday and if you go to actually,
我记得是。
go to page 31, I believe.
是的，这一页，如果你往下看，
Yeah it's a page and if you go down,
这就是内存，
this is whats the memory,
它会写出内存映射，在电路板上，
it will spell out the memory map is, of the board
我们会看到在地址 0 ，
and we'll see at address zero
0 是预留的，那里什么都没有。
zero is reserved nothing is there.
如果你往下滚动这张内存映射图，
If you go scroll down in this memory map,
你会看到关于映射的
you'll see some information about all
所有不同事物的一些信息，
the different things that are mapped,
例如，以太网板映射到 OX1 ，
for example, ethernet board is mapped
你知道，0x 的一个地址。
at Ox1, you know, 0x something.
如果你可以再往下一点的话，太往下了。
If you might go further down, oops, too much down.
在这里，你可以看到 0x8000 的条目效，
Here, you see the entry for 0x8000 worked
这实际上是 DDR 内存，
and that actually is DDR memory,
片外易失性存储器，
the Off-Chip Volatile Memory, so
所以这些是 DRAM 芯片，
those are the DRAM chips or
我可以在上一张幻灯片上展示给你看。
I can show you on the previous slide.
所以，保持头脑清醒是很好的，
And so it's just good to keep your head correct
即使我们在和 QEMU 交互，
even though we're talking to
你是在使用软件，
QEMU, you're overseeing software in
但最终一切都是由
the end everything is determined,
实际的电路板会决定的。
by you know the actual board.
好的，回到我的幻灯片。
Okay, so go back to a my slides.
那我们来看一下布局。
So let's look at the layout.
好的，诺亚，说吧。
Yeah, Noah, go ahead.
您说这个布局
Yeah, when you say that this
是由硬件决定的，
this layout is determined by the
具体是指
hardware, do you specifically mean
CPU 本身
like the CPU itself or the
还是 CPU 所在的板。
board on which the CPU resides.
是 CPU 所在的板，对的。
The board which the CPU resides,
因为这块板，
correct. Because you know the borad,
你知道， CPU 是中间
you know, the CPU is the
那个正方形的
grey thing in the middle that
灰色东西，比如 RISC-V ，
square thing, saying whatever RISC-V,
DRAM 芯片
the DRAM chips are sitting off,
在处理器旁边，
the off the processor correct, it's
是电路板设计师
the board designers who put the
把芯片、 DRAM 和很多 IO 设备
chip the DRAM, you know, do many
放在一起。
IO devices altogether.
操作系统的
And large part of
很大一部分
an operating system is actually,
是 CPU ，但
you know the CPU is one part, but the
IO 设备也同样重要，
IO devices are at least as
对吧，所以
important, right, and so when you're
当你编写操作系统时，
writing an operating system you both
你既要处理 CPU ，
have to deal with the CPU
也要处理 IO 设备，
as well as you know with the IO devices,
你知道，你想要
you know and you want to
通过互联网发送数据包，
send a packet over the Internet.
总得有人来接手。
Well, somebody has to take over.
你知道网络驱动程序，
You know the network driver,
网卡来发送数据包，
the NIC card to actually do that,
这就是操作系统。
and that's the operating system.
所以回到
So going back to the right
这张图片的右侧，
side of this picture,
这是物理地址布局，
which is the physical address layout,
正如我在
you know we see basically the
文档中显示的，
bottom was unused as I showed
底部是未使用的。
you on that document.
物理地址
It turns out that
0x1000 ，
0x1000, that physical address,
是引导 ROM 所在的位置，
that's where the boot ROM
所以当你打开那块板时，
is, so when you turn on that board,
首先发生的就是
the first thing that happens is
引导 ROM 编码开始进行。
actually coding the boot ROM runs.
当启动 ROM 完成时，
And when the boot rom is
它实际上会跳到
done it actually will jump to
这个 0x000 地址，
this 0x000 and it's
这是操作系统的工作，
a job of the operating system make
确保那里有
sure that there's some,
一些数据。
you know, some data there.
然后还有一堆
And then there's a bunch of
其他的设备
other devices that will talk about
与中断控制器交互，
goes to interrupt controller,
我们将在下周讨论这个问题。
we'll talk about it next week.
有一个 CLENT ，
There's a CLENT, another part
是关于中断的另一个故事，
of the interrupt story that we'll
我们会在下周讨论，
talk about next week,
所以有多个设备可以生成中断，
so there's multiple devices can generate
需要计划将
interrupts there needs to be planned
这些中断路由到
to route those interrupts to the
适当的请求级别，
to the appropriate request level and
这都是由中断控制器
it's all implemented by those
实现的。
interrupt controllers.
在回答问题之前，
And let me finish for
让我把这个说完，
a second you know this,
你知道，
this slide before
就是这张张幻灯片。
answering question.
然后有一个
Then there's a uart
UART 设备，
that was the device,
这实际上是
that was actually the thing that actually,
UART 设备与
the device actually UART device actually
控制台和显示器交互，
interacts with the console and the
然后是
display and then there's the VIRTIO
VIRTIO 磁盘.
there's the disk.
这就是设备，
And that's the device,
它属于，
there's a device belong,
它实际上是与磁盘交互的。
it's that actually interacts with the disk.
所以当你
And so when you write to
往地址写入时，比如，
location to address, let's say,
0x200 ，然后
0x200 then
该物理地址
that physical address corresponds to the
对应于 CLINT ，因此你想要
CLINT and so do you want
执行存储指令
to do store instruction,
加载指令
load instruction,
对实现 CLINT 的芯片
your reading and writing to the
进行读取和写入。
chip that implements the CLINT.
我们稍后会看到
We'll see later what that exactly
这到底意味着什么，
means but basically you can think
但你可以认为
about this as interacting directly with
这是直接与设备交互，
the device and not reading or
而不是读或写物理内存。
writing physical memory.
是的，我有个问题。
Yeah there's a question.
我只是想确认
So just trying to make
0x800 以下的地址
sure the addresses below
并不存在于 DRAM 中。
0x800, they don't really exist in DRAM.
如果我们访问这些地址时，
If when we mention those addresses
我们会直接访问其他硬件。
we directly go to the other hardwares.
是的，
Yeah yeah,
所以如果你回到这张照片。
so if you go back to this picture.
任何大于
Anything of above
0x8000 的，
0x8000, correct，
这些就是 DRAM 芯片。
That's these DRAM chips.
你知道我画不出，
And you know I can't
我不能给你
draw, I can't point you
指出 CLINT ，
to the CLINT,
但我一般都听说过的，
but like generally hears that,
比如以太网。
ethernet.
这是一个特定的
And so that's a particular physical
物理地址，
address and we can write you
我们可以写入加载存储指令，
know load store instructions is called
也称为内存映射 IO ，
memory mapped IO,
我们可以加载和存储指令，
we can load and store instructions,
我们可以对以太网控制器编程。
we can program ethernet controller.
我也有一个问题，
I also have a question,
为什么上面的这一大块
why was this big chunk at
写着没有使用。
the top says unused.
为什么没有使用。好的，
Why is it not used. OK,
记住，
so remember,
不是每台机器都有
not every machine not
2 的 56 次方字节的
every so there's 2 to the power 56,
物理地址空间，
bytes physical address space,
如果你不想的话，
but you don't have those,
你不需要
you know, plug in that much memory
那么多内存
into the board,
插到电路板上。
if you don't want to.
所以，它的一些部分
And so some parts of it
可能是未使用的，
may be unused, depending on how
这取决于你在电路板上
much you're DRAM chips are sitting
有多少 DRAM 芯片。
on the board.
事实上，在 xv6 中，
In fact, they like in xv6,
我想我们把内存限制在
we I think limit ourselves to
128 兆字节。
128 megabyte.
仅此而已。
And no more.
那么，
So when a, when a
当加载存储指令
load store instruction goes out of
从 CPU 发出时，会不会发生，
the CPU, does that go,
比如它从哪里
like where does it get
路由到正确的 IO ，
routed to the correct IO, like
比如已经从 CPU
already from the CPU,
路由到正确的 IO ，
so kind of like if the
在 CPU 发出指令之前，
CPU before it sends it out
它保证
it says OK,
如果小于 0x8000 ，
if it's lower than 0x8 and all the zeros then
那么我会将其
I'm going to send it to
发送到正确的 IO 设备，
the correct IO devices,
否则我会
and then otherwise I'm going to
将其发送给内存，
send it to the to the
比如 DRAM 芯片。
memory like DRAM chip.
是的，你可以把它想象成
Yeah, you can think about as
一个安装在 RISC-V 内部的
a demultiplexer sitting on the
多路分解器，
inside of the RISC-V, you
你知道，块。
know block.
哦，那么它已经在
Oh, so it's inside of
那个块里面了。好的。
that block. OK.
作为存储控制器并进行路由。
As a memory controller and does routing.
因为非常重要，
Because very important to have
你要把这一切都弄清楚。
that sort of all clear in your head.
还好吗，
Are you okay,
现在我想
so now I want to
换到这张图片的右边。
switch to the right side of this picture.
这就是 xv6
And this is basically what
设置的，
xv6 sets up, to
虚拟地址空间，
the virtual address space, that
xv6 设置，
xv6 setup,
所以当机器启动时，
so when the machine boot, there's
还没有页面可用，
no page enable yet,
xv6 设置了
xv6 sets up
第一个页表，
the first page tables, virtual
虚拟地址空间，
address space and that's actually
这实际上是内核使用的
the virtual address space
虚拟地址空间，
the kernel uses and we'll look
我们稍后会看到它。
at it in the second.
在代码中，
At the code, but,
这就是布局，
and this is the layout
你知道，
and it turns out, you know,
因为我们想让 xv6
because we want to keep
尽可能简单，
xv6 as simple as possible,
让你很容易理解。
it's easy for you to understand.
从虚拟到物理的映射。
The mapping from virtual to physical
主要是恒等映射。
is mostly in identity mapping.
这意味着
So basically what that means is
虚拟地址 0x200
that the virtual address 0x200
映射到物理地址 0x200 ，
maps to physical address
内核将
0x200, the kernel
完全按照这种方式
will set up the page tables
设置页表，
exactly in that way,
这意味着
and so that means basically that
此顶部下面的
you know all virtual addresses,
所有虚拟地址。
below this top.
这是物理内存的
Which is the top of
顶部，与右侧
physical memory are identical to the
实际使用的物理地址
physical addresses that are actually being
相同。
used on the right side.
这就是为什么
And so this is why all
所有的箭头都是直的，
the arrows are straight, because it's
因为这是恒等映射。
identity mapping.
对于这一点的小的变化，
The small changes to this,
有两件重要的事情要提。
there are two important things to mention.
Amiar ，稍等一下，
Amiar, hold on a second, while
我先说一下
try to first mention the two
这两件重要的事情。
important things to mention.
首先，
First of all,
有一些页面，
there's some pages,
一些映射在
some maps very high up in
内存中非常高。
your memory.
其中一些页面在内存中的
Which some pages very high
位置非常高，
up in memory,
例如内核堆栈
for example the stack a
实际也映射到
kernel stack actually sits up is
内存位置较高的位置。
also map high up in memory.
内存较高的原因
And the reason is high
是因为我们在
up in memory is because we
它下面有一个
have a guard page below it
未映射的保护页。
that is not mapped.
因此，
So the PTE entry below
内核堆栈下面的
the kernel stack, of one of
PTE条目，
the kernel stack [], does
没有设置有效位。
have, not have it's valid bit set.
而且，如果内核
And, so if you know, the kernel
在堆栈之外运行，
runs off its stack and will
会导致页面错误，
result in a page fault,
这比在内核拥有的
which is better than basically scribbling
其他内存上乱涂乱画
over some other memory that the
要好得多。
kernel has.
你会直接得到异常，
You get immediate panic,
你知道有些东西堆积起来是不好的。
you know that something's bad to stack.
当然，我们不想
Of course, we don't want
浪费物理内存，
to waste physical memory and so
所以当我们这样做的时候，
when we do that by basically
基本上是把堆栈放得很高，
putting the stack high, um,
在它下面放一个保护页，
a guard page, an empty guard
一个空的保护 PTE 条目。
PTE entry below it.
而且守卫页面
And the guard page
实际上并不会消耗任何物理内存，
doesn't really consume any physical memory
它位于
records sitting high up in the
虚拟地址空间高处，
virtual address space,
所以没有消耗任何东西。
so nothing is being consumed.
但这意味着，在这种情况下
But that means that they're showing
堆栈页面
this case, stack page,
被映射了两次。
for example is mapped twice.
它被映射到一个
It's mapped at a high
很高的地址，也被直接映射到
address and it's mapped directly
一个 PHYSTOP
by one of the dresses
下面的地址。
that below PHYSTOP.
所以你可以这样做，
And so you can do, this
这是你可以用
is one example of all the
页表来做的
sort of cool things, you can
很酷的事情的一个例子，
do with page tables,
你可以映射一个物理地址两次，
you can map a physical address twice,
你可以不映射一个物理地址，
you cannot map a physical address,
你知道
you know it can be
可以是一对一映射，
one to one mapping, one to
一对多映射，多对一映射，
many mapping, many to one mapping,
所有这些事情都是可能的。
all that kind of stuff is possible.
实际上它用的很多，
Actually it does really use
有几个地方
many of them, but there's a
我们用到了这些技巧。
couple places we use those tricks.
保护页面中的堆栈
And there's the stack in
就是一个例子，
the guard page is one
这是 xv6 用来
example, of one of the
跟踪 bug 的
cool trick then xv6 uses
一个很酷的技巧。
mostly to track down bugs.
我想提的第二件事
The second thing I wanted to
是权限。
mention is that, the permissions.
例如内核文本，
So, for example the kernel text,
内核文本的页面
the pages for the kernel text
被映射为 R-X ，这意味着
are mapped R-X, meaning you can
你可以读取并执行它。
read it and execute it.
但是你不能写入内核文本，
But you cannot write to
同样，
kernel text and again this
这个位是空的。
is basically devoid,
我们尽早捕捉到 bug ，
[bugs] we catch
内核数据当然
them early, kernel data of course
需要能够被写入，
needs to be able to be
所以
written to, and so it has
它映射了读写，
mapped read write,
但是你不能执行
but you cannot execute
内核数据页的指令。
out of kernel data pages instructions.
所以执行位没有设置。
So the execute bit is not set.
这个能理解吗？
Does that make sense.
我跳过了一两个问题，
I skipped one or two questions,
如果这些问题还没有回答，
so if these questions are still
现在可以提问。
not answered, please ask them.
我们在聊天中有一个问题。
We have a question in the chat.
我们是否有
Do we have multiple kernel stacks
多个内核堆栈用于不同的进程，比如
for different processes like we have
n 个 kstack 用于 n 个进程。
n kstacks for n processes.
答案是肯定的。
And answers yes.
因此，每个进程，每个用户进程
So every process every user process
都有一个对应的内核堆栈。
has a corresponding kernel stack.
稍后我会
I will see that in a
看到这一点。
little bit later.
好的，那么让我，
Okay, so let me,
Samir ，说吧。
Samir, go ahead.
那么另一个应用程序的
So what's the virtual memory
虚拟内存映射到
of another application
物理内存中
map to somewhere in the physical
未使用的空间或。
memory in the unused space or.
是的，一个非常好的观点，
Yes, a very good point,
所以有一堆
so there's a bunch of
物理内存，
physical memory,
是的，这是空闲内存。
correct, here's free memory.
这里也有
Um, that's free memory
空闲内存，对，
here too, right, and
我们使用
we use that actually use
这些空闲内存来
that free memory to basically
存储页表的页面，
store pages of page tables,
用户进程，以及
user processes as well as you
用户进程的
know the text and data of
文本和数据。
user level processes.
如果我们在
And if we are on many many,
很多用户进程上，
many user processes at some point
在某个时候我们会用完空闲内存，
we'll run out of free memory,
然后 fork 或 exec
and then basically fork or exec
会返回一个错误。
will return an error.
但这意味着
But that means that the
进程的虚拟空间
virtual space for processes are
比内核的虚拟空间
much smaller than the virtual
小得多，是吗？
space for the kernel, right?
虚拟空间的大小
Well, the virtual spaces as
理论上是一样的，
the same as the same size in principle,
但是会比较少。
but it will be less populated.
然后让我们来
Then let me let's look at
看一些代码，
some code,
我认为所有这些东西
and I think that all this
都会变得更清楚。
stuff becomes a bit more clear.
我有个小问题，
I just want small thing,
有很多，比如
is so given that a lot of the like,
每个进程都有
each process has a big part
很大一部分内存
of the memory map to the
映射到相同的位置，是否可以通过
same location, is that optimized by
将其合并到一个映射的位置
like consolidating that into one place
进行优化。
that mapping or no.
嗯，这很好，
Um, it's good,
xv6 没有做这个，
xv6 does not do that,
比如 page table 实验中的
like one of the challenge
挑战练习之一
exercises in the page table lab
就是实现它。
is to actually implement that.
我明白了。真正的操作系统
I see. The real operating system
会做到这一点。
would do that.
嗯。了解了。
Yeah. Makes sense.
问得好。
Very good question.
我想一旦你有了页表，
I think you get a sense
你就会明白
of what all kinds of things
什么事情都是可能的。
are possible, once you have page tables.
好的，
Okay,
让我们开始常做的事，
so let's do the usual thing,
再一次启动 xv6 ，
boot xv6 again and again,
你知道 QEMU 用来
you know QEMU uses basically implementing
模拟电路板。
the board.
让我们，糟糕， -gdb ，
And you know let's. Oops, -gdb,
上一次我们看了
last time we looked at
路由是如何
how the routing happens correct
发生的，
and then we got to
然后我们到了 main ，
main and then basically one
然后是内核，
of the things that, the kernel,
其中一个函数 kvminit ，
when one of the functions called
它实际上为内核
kvminit and that actually
设置了地址空间。
sets up the address space for the kernel.
我们在上一张幻灯片的
And so we saw in the
图片中看到，
picture where in the previous slide,
你知道，
what that you know looks like
现在我们开始，
and here we go,
C 编码是如何实际设置的。
C code how it actually is being set up.
还有为什么，等等，
And why, hold on, something's
有些东西没像我想的那样。
not going as I wanted to.
我找对目录了吗？
Am I the right directories.
等一下，
Hold on a second here
我正在想办法
while I'm trying to sort
解决我的问题。
out my problems.
那很好。
That is good.
我的意思是正确的目录，
I mean the right directory,
是的，我们想在
yeah, We want to set a
main 设置一个中断，
break from the main just
为了确保。
to make sure.
很好，然后是 kvminit 的中断点。
Good, and then a break point at kvminit.
实际上我现在可以
Actually I can just step to
单步运行它了，下一个是 consoleinit
it now, next consoleinit
printfinit，
printfinit,
你知道，我们之前已经看到了，
you know, we saw it before,
物理内存分配器。
physical memory allocator.
你知道吗，发生了一些
You know, something happens that I
我意想不到的事情。
not expecting.
这是怎么回事。
What is going on.
我们在讲课前运行是正确的。
We're gonna run this right before
这里，
lecture. Here,
这就是实际打印的情况，
that's what's going on actually printing,
好的。
Okay.
有意思。
Interesting.
好吧，再来一次，
Okay one more time,
看看我会不会更幸运[]。
see if I can get lucky more [].
非常好。
Very good.
继续，希望它能到达那里，
Continue, hopefully it will get there,
稍等片刻。很好，
wait a little bit. Okay great
我们在 kvminit ，
we're at the kvminit,
所以现在这个函数，
so basically we're now this function
在 emacs 缓冲区的右边，
here, on the right side in
你可以看到它。
the emacs buffer, you can see it.
而且，
And,
我想我稍微修改了一下函数，
I think I've modified function
我希望我是这样做的。
slightly I hope I did.
我想我做过了，
I think I did, we'll
我们拭目以待，
see, and what we knew
我们将进入函数。
is going to walk step into the function.
给我拆分布局，
Give me layout split it's
这样更容易看到。
easier to see.
你可以看到的
And this is the first thing
第一件事，是
that you can see, this section
当前的这一部分
of the current actually allocates a
实际上为顶级页面目录
physical page, for the top level
分配了一个物理页面。
page directory.
然后将其置零，
And then zeroes it
使得所有 PTE 条目都为零。
out so that all the PTE entries are zero.
然后开始在每个设备，
And then basically starts mapping in
IO 设备中逐个映射。
every device, IO device one by one.
例如， UART0 ，它开始
And so, for example, the UART0, it
将映射映射到
basically starts mapping maps that into
内核地址空间，
the kernel address space and so
我们可以看到一个
we can look at a file
名为 memlayout.h 的文件，
called memlayout.h, is basically translate
它将文档中展示的第 31 页
page 31 that I showed
转换成我们
you from the document into a
正在使用的一系列常量。
bunch of constants that we're using.
对于 UART0 ，这里是
And so, for example here it says what
地址 0x1000 。
the address of 0x1000 is.
嗯，你有什么想法。
Um, [do you ideas].
所以，
And so,
我们可以
you know, we can basically
通过调用
map it into the address space
这个函数 kvmmap
by calling this function
将其映射到地址空间，
kvmmap which I will look in
我稍后会看到这个函数。
a second.
然后，
And then,
在 page table 实验的
in the first exercise of
第一个练习中，
the page table lab,
要求你实现一个
you are asked to implement a
名为 vmprint 的函数。
function called vmprint.
我也实现了它，
Um, and I implemented it too,
我将调试它，
and I'm going to step over
我们将看到，
it and we'll see basically,
页表，内核页表，
page tables, kernel page table as it
它是在对 kvmmap 的
is set up after that one
一次调用之后设置的，
call to the kvmmap,
这是我要做的。
so I'm going to do that.
我们要打印
And we're going to print
一些东西。
out something.
我们要看一下
And so we're going to
这里的输出，
look a little bit of the output here,
这是页表，
so here's the page table that
它是
is the
顶层的物理地址，
physical address of the top level,
页面目录，
page directory,
实际上位于
so the thing that actually sits
satp 寄存器中。
in satp, or will sit in satp.
然后我们有了
And then we have
顶级页面的条目 0 ，
entry 0 of the top
其中有
level page really has one
一个 PTE 条目。
PTE entry in it.
那就是
And that is the contains
包含中级页表目录的
the physical address for the middle
物理地址。
level page table directory.
中间页面目录
The middle page level directory has
有一个条目，即 128 。
one entry namely 128.
它指向页表目录的底部，
And that points to the bottom
并且
of page table directory and the
底部的页表目录有
bottom page table directory has the
用于物理页面的条目。
entry then for the physical page.
你可以看到，
And you can see,
实际上，你知道
indeed that the physical address,
该底层的物理地址
you know for that bottom level
是 0x1000 ，
is 0x1000
对应于 UART0 。
corresponding to uart0.
对，虚拟地址
Right, so basically virtual address
1000 转换成
1000 translates
物理地址 1000 。
to physical address [1000].
我们可以再次确定，
We can sure double check,
这确实是合法的。
this is indeed all legit.
根据，
By,
我们取那个地址 0x10000000L ，
and let's take that address 0x100L
我们将右移 12 位。
and we're going to shift 12.
这应该是，
And that should be,
你知道的，
you know, that gives the top
得到最高级别的 27 位。
level 27 bits.
我们再右移 9 位，
We shifted 9,
所以我取 0x10000 ，
so I'm gonna take 0x100,
我们可以右移 9 位，
0x10000, and we can
并打印出来。
shift at 9, print that.
那就是 0x80 ，
And that is 0x80,
实际上把 0x80
and actually print 0x80
打印成一个十进制数字，
as a decimal number, it's
它将是 128 ，好的。
going to be 128, OK.
所以我们看到，
So we see actually sort of
实际上，你知道，
you know it all sort of
这一切都是有意义的。
makes sense.
我们还看到
We also see I printed out
这里打印出了标志位，
the flags here,
最下面的级别是
and you know the bottom
读取、写入和有效，
level has read,
因为 valid 是 1 。
write and valid, because valid is one.
有关于这个的问题吗？
Any questions about this.
好的，那么。
Okay, so.
内核继续
The kernel basically proceeds, you know
用这种方式
doing setting up the whole address
设置整个地址空间。
space in this way.
因此，我们
And, so we've called
为 VIRTIO 调用 kvmmap ，也为
kvmmap for VIRTIO, for the
CLINT ， PLIC 调用。
CLINT, for the PLIC.
映射内核文本，
Maps the kernel text, maps
映射内核内存或内核数据，
the kernel memory or kernel data,
然后映射 TRAMPOLINE 页，
and then the TRAMPOLINE page that
这个我们将在下周讨论。
we'll talk about next week.
实际上我们
And so in fact we
可以单步运行，
can single step through this and
然后看看最终的页面目录
then see what the final page
是什么样子。
directory looks like.
嗯，下一个，下一个。
Um, so next next next next.
基本上，设置 TRAMPOLINE ，
Basically, you know set the TRAMPOLINE,
现在我们要
so now we're going to print
打印完整的页表目录。
the complete page table directory.
我们看到
You know we see basically
很多 PTE 正在设置中。
lot of PTE is actually being setup.
我不会
And I'm not going to
详细讨论，
talk about in any detail,
但是您知道，基本上是
but you know basically fills
填充页目录
out the page
来实际创建
directory to actually create
虚拟映射，
virtual mapping that we
就像我们在上一张幻灯片中看到的那样。
basically saw on the previous slide.
我下一步要做的
When I expect what I
事情是
wanna do next is actually
更有趣的。
much more interesting.
是的，我要做的是。
Yeah I'm gonna.
是的，我想去这里，
Yeah I wanna go here,
实际上，我猜我可能
actually, I guess maybe I already
已经这样做了，第 21 行，
did this, were 21,
不，我在第 21 行，好的，单步执行一下。
no, I'm 21, okay so single step that.
好吧，那太糟糕了，
OK that's too bad, I
我已经过去了。但基本上是这样。
got past it. But basically,
让我再运行一遍。
let me, let me restart this.
我要在 kvminithart 的设置断点。
I wanna break point at kvminithart.
然后继续，
And continue,
我们现在在 kvminithart ，
are now here at kvminithart,
你可以看到，
and you see here,
我们正在写入
basically that we're writing the
satp 寄存器，
satp register,
所以基本上内核
so basically the kernel is going
将启用页表或
to enable page table or
硬件， MMU ，
the hard, MMU,
开始使用
to basically start using
我们刚刚设置的页表。
the page table that we just set up.
还有一个有趣的问题。
And one interesting question.
好的，再次切换到
Okay, so they do have layout
拆分布局，
split again,
所以，
So,
这里的某个地方将会，
somewhere here is going to be,
这是一条指令，
here's the instruction in,
在执行这条指令后，
so once, something really dramatic happens
发生了一些非常戏剧性的事情。
after executing this instruction.
是的，我完全可以
Um, let's say yeah I can
看到相同的指令，
see the same instruction exactly but
但是在这个范围内，
there's this this extent,
一旦执行了这条指令，
once this instruction is executed what
下一个要转换的地址
will happen with the next address
会发生什么。
that's being translated.
在我们
Well, at the point that
执行这条指令
we execute this instruction, before
之前，
executing this instruction,
还没有启用页表，
there's no page tables enabled yet
所以没有发生转换。
so no translation happens.
但是下一次，
But the next and then the
程序计数器更新为 4 。
program counter is updated by [4].
然后执行下一条指令，
And then the next instruction is
并且将使用
executed and the program counter will
虚拟页、页表存储器
be translated using the virtual page,
来转换程序计数器。
page table memory.
所以这是，
And so this is, you
思考这个问题的方式，
know, the ways to think about this,
这是一个激动人心的时刻。
this is a dramatic moment.
因为整个地址转换
Because basically the whole address translation,
都开始启用，
they started to enable and
每个地址都可能
every address needs no maybe
潜在会有所不同。
potentially something different.
因为在我们运行
Right, because before we're running your
物理地址之前，
physical addresses,
然后是页表，
then the page table,
还没有安装，
haven't install, and whatever is in
无论映射中有什么，
the mapping,
现在都有了
now there's now the new meaning
虚拟地址的新含义。
of a virtual address.
这就是它的工作原理，
And here's how this works
你知道，
out, you know, the fact that
这个实际工作是值得注意的，
this actually works out is remarkable
因为就像下一条指令一样，
because like the next instruction,
下一个值是一个虚拟地址，
the next value is a virtual
而不是一个物理地址。
address and not a physical address.
下一条指令是这个，
The next instruction is going to
是 0x80001110 。
be this, whatever 0x1110.
为什么这会成功呢。
And why does this work out.
原因是因为
And the reason works out is
内核已经设置好了，
because the kernel is setup,
我们可以标识页面映射。
we can identity page mapping. So,
因此，在我们启用虚拟分页硬件之后，
after we enable the virtual paging hardware,
我们知道这个转换器将再次
we actually know this translator will
转换为相同的物理地址，
translate again to the same physical
因此我们实际上将结束
address and so indeed we'll actually end up, you know,
执行写入指令，
executing the writing instruction, because that's
因为这正是
actually exactly the instruction,
虚拟硬件编程
the memory location that the virtual
所针对的指令和内存位置。
hardware is programmed for.
这个能理解吗？
So does this make sense.
同样，虚拟内存编程困难的
Again, one reason why programming virtual
一个原因是，
memory is difficult is because once
一旦执行了这些 satp 指令，
you execute one of these satp
你就在 satp 寄存器中
instructions you load a page table
加载了页表，
in the satp register, your world
你的世界就完全不同了。
completely changes.
现在，每个地址都会使用
And every address is now translated
你设置的页表进行转换。
with the page table, that you set up.
那么，如果页表设置不正确
And so what happens if the
会发生什么呢？
page table setup incorrectly.
你会怎么做，可能会发生什么。
What would you, what might happen.
有人想回答这个问题吗，
Anybody who wants to
或者在聊天中回答，
say that answered or answered in
可以等待。
the chat, you can wait.
你可以覆盖内核数据。
You could override kernel data.
是的，你可以覆盖内核数据，
Yeah you could overwrite kernel data
还有其他可能发生的事情，
what else could happen,
页面错误，
yeah page fault, you basically do,
映射可能是不正确的，
the mapping may be incorrect and
地址完全可以转换，
basically the address can be translated at all,
所以内核可以，
and so the kernel can, you
你知道，硬件不会这样做，
know, the hardware won't do it
通常内核会停顿和死机。
and usally the kernel there stops and panics.
这个能理解吗？
Does that make sense,
所以
so if you get a bug
如果您的页表中有 bug ，
in your page tables,
你会看到这些
you know you're going to see
错误或崩溃信息。
these are errors or crashes.
所以，
And so,
下一个实验，
one reason that example, the next lab,
今晚分发或发布的
that page table lab, that
page table 实验，
will hand out or release tonight,
会很难，
is going to be hard,
因为那些 bug 会出现。
because those kind of bugs will show up.
如果你不够小心，
If you're not careful enough or
或者你还没有完全理解某些方面。
you haven't fully internalized some aspect yet.
你基本上
And you're basically going to
会遇到内核崩溃，
get kernel crash and
你会很艰难，
you're gonna have a hard
需要花一些时间、
time when you will take a little bit of time
精力和调试工作
and energy and detective work
来追踪发生这种情况的原因。
to basically track down why that happened.
这只是
And that's just the, that's just
虚拟内存编程的一部分。
part of like programming virtual memory.
因为它是如此强大，
Because it's such a
你知道，
powerful primitive, you know, you
如果你弄错了，
get it wrong,
会产生严重的后果。
you're gonna have powerful consequences.
然而，另一方面是非常有趣的，
Yet the other hand is great amount of fun,
所以我不想以负面结束。
so I don't want to end on a negative node,
但所有这些都会
But all that will give
让你真正理解什么是
you a real understanding of actually
真正的虚拟内存，
what really virtual memory is and
以及它能做什么。
what it can do.
好的，我想
Okay I think I'm running
时间不多了，
out of time so I'm
所以到此为止了，
gonna stop here,
这样大家有时间
so people have time to
去下一节课或下一个活动，
go to the next class or next activity,
但是如果你们还有什么问题，
but if you have any questions
请稍等，然后继续提问。
left, please hang on and ask them.
我们下周一见。
And, we'll see you on monday.
祝你们顺利完成 syscall 实验。
And good luck with finishing the syscall lab.
我有一个关于 walk 的问题，
Um, hi, I have a question about walk,
在代码中，
so it says and in the code,
它返回的 PTE 的第一个表。
it returns the like the first tables of PTE.
是的。
Yeah right.
但是它是怎么工作的，
But how does it work,
比如其他函数
then like the other functions when
它们期望 PTE
they expect the actual PTE,
而不是物理地址。
than the physical address.
基本上这会返回
Yeah basically this returns the PTE
页表中的 PTE 条目，
entry in the page table,
内核可以
and the kernel can read or
读取或写入页表条目。
write page table entries.
现在你可以
Um, and so now you can
把值放到 PTE 里。
stick values into the PTE.
也许我可以画一幅图，
And so maybe I can draw
来帮助解释这个问题。
a picture that is helpful.
让我们看看。
Let's see.
所以我们有一个页面目录。
So maybe we have a page directory.
而且，这个 walk 代码，
And, you know, this walk code,
页面目录中有 512 个 PTE 。
so the page directory has 512 PTE in it.
从 0 到 511 ，函数的作用是
Here's zero, here's 511 and basically what the
返回一个指向其中一个 PTE 的指针。
function does it returns a pointer to one of these PTEs.
这只是一个虚拟地址，
And so that's just a virtual address,
它指向那个特定的 PTE 。
and it points to that particular PTE.
现在内核可以，
And now the kernel can, you
通过向它写入值，
know manipulate that PTE, by whatever
来操纵那个 PTE 。
writing values to it.
比如某个物理地址，
Like some physical address,
也许有一些权限
maybe with some permissions
在它的后十位。
into it for the bottom ten bits.
然后更新页表目录，
And then basically updates the page table directory,
稍后将数据加载到 satp 中时，
and then later on when you load data into satp,
这一修改将会生效。
now, that affect that change will go into effect.
这个能理解吗？
Does that make sense.
是的，理解了，
Yeah that makes sense, I guess
我想我只是搞不懂，
I just confused like why does
为什么它要一直转到第三个页表，
it do the work of going all the way to the third,
然后只返回第一个 PTE 。
page table and then only return the first PTE.
不是，返回的实际上是最底层的。
No, return is actually the bottom one.
实际上，我讲详细一点，
Actually, let me be careful,
如果它通过了 n 级，
if, you know, it goes through
从 2 级开始，然后到 1 级，
the n levels, started level 2 and then go to level 1,
再到 0 级。
again a level 0.
如果 alloc 位设置，但是这个级别不存在，
If the alloc bit set and level doesn't exist,
将会创建中间页表目录。
it will create the intermediate page table directory.
把它清零，然后继续查找。
And zero it out and then keep going to look.
所以，你总是落在最底层 PTE 。
So, you always end up on the bottom PTE.
如果 alloc 位没有设置，
If alloc not set, you stop
你会在第一个 PTE 停止，它没有值。
at the first PTE, that doesn't have value.
好的，理解了，
Okay, that makes sense,
实际得到的是最后一个。
this is the last one, the actual on gonna have.
好的，谢谢。
Okay okay, thank you.
还有其他问题吗？
Any other questions.
我有一个问题，
So I have a question,
前面都能理解，
basically everything made sense until
直到我们将内核的虚拟地址
we mapped the virtual addresses
映射到物理地址，
to, of the kernel to the physical addresses.
我的理解是，
So my understanding is that
每个进程都会有自己的页表，
each process will have its own page table,
它也是一个三级表，
which is also a three level tree
将其虚拟地址映射到物理地址，
which wraps its virtual addresses to physical addresses,
但然后我们将内核虚拟地址
but then we map the kernel
映射到物理地址，
virtual addresses to physical addresses, I
我认为我们没有考虑到
don't think we accounted for the
[实际的内核虚拟内存]
actual tree of them virtual addresses of the kernel
或其他进程将拥有其虚拟地址的位置。
or where other processes will have their virtual addresses.
虚拟地址
And I'm sorry, virtual addresses like
就像虚拟[表树]，
the virtual table trees and
[页表树]指向
whatever the page table tree points
物理内存。
at in the physical memory.
是的，
Yeah, so yeah so so you're
所以回到这张关于内核的幻灯片，
back this is slide with kernel,
虚拟内核地址空间，
address space, virtual kernel address
当内核分配特定进程的
space and so when the kernel allocates proc,
proc 和页表时，
and page tables for that particular process, they're going
它们将被分配到内存这里，
to be allocated at memory here, memory is
内存还没有被使用。
not being used yet.
内核将进行编程，
And the kernel is going to
我们可能会为页表
program, we'll probably allocate a
分配几个页面，
couple pages for the page table,
远离普通进程，
off the usual process and
并填充 [PTE] 。
will fill in the PTEs.
在内核运行该进程的
And at some point when the
某个时刻，
kernel runs that process,
它将加载路由，
it will load the route,
加载这些页分配的
physical address for those pages that
物理地址，
is allocated for that page table
或页表，
or basically page table then built
然后将其构建到 satp 寄存器中。
into the satp register.
这时，
And at that point the processor
处理器将运行在虚拟地址空间，
will run with the virtual address
那是内核为
space that the kernel constructed for
该特定进程构造的。
that particular process.
所以
So the kernel gave up
内核为进程释放了一些内存，
some of its memory for processes,
在理论上进程的虚拟空间
and then the virtual space in theory is as big
和内核一样大，
for the process as the kernel,
但在现实中，不是那样的。
but in reality, it's really not.
这里有一张
Yeah, have a picture with the layout
普通进程的
of a virtual address space with
虚拟地址空间布局图片，
their usual level process and again
它也是从 0 到 MAXVA 。
it goes from zero to MAXVA.
就像内核地址空间一样，
In the same way as the
它有
kernel address space does and it's
自己的一组页表
basically has his own set of
来映射这些
page tables to map those translation
内核设置的转换。
the kernel setup.
但是我们不能实际使用所有的 MAXVA 虚拟地址。
But we can't actually use all of the MAXVA virtual.
是的，我们不能。
No, we cannot.
我们的内存用完了。
We run out of memory.
因此，许多进程
So many of the processes are much smaller than
比所有虚拟地址空间都要小得多。
all of the virtual address space.
我理解了，谢谢。
I see, thank you.
我有一个问题，
I've got a quick question,
你能不能回到 walk 代码，
could you go back to the walk code,
好的，当然可以。
yeah yeah absolutely.
这是我最喜欢的功能之一。
It's one of my favorite functions.
所以我想，
So I guess, one
有一件事我很困惑，
thing I'm confused about is after
那就是在你写到 satp 寄存器之后，
you write to the satp register, can the kernel even access
内核甚至可以直接访问物理地址，
physical addresses directly,
所以
so it looks like in the
在它正在转换的代码中，
code that it's converting you know
比如页设置为物理地址，
like page was being set to a physical address,
但是如果已经设置了 satp ，
but if satp is set,
那不会被解释为虚拟地址吗？
won't that be interpreted as a virtual address.
是的，
Yeah,
所以，让我们来看一下 hartinit 。
so, okay so let's look at hartinit.
内置在内核地址空间中。
That's kvm, so built in kernel address space.
对于内核页表，
The kernel page table,
最初，
initially, the virtual physical, address
地址被转换为物理地址，
is translated to a physical
并且该地址被写入到 satp 寄存器中。
address and that's actually written into the satp register.
在这一点，
And at that point you
我们使用的是
know we're running with the address
在此之前构建的地址空间，
space that we've constructed right before
比如运行 kvminit 。
here, this kvminit.
给了我一张映射，
And gave me a map is
基本上就是
basically nothing else than calling
对每一个这个范围的地址
walk for every address where
调用 walk 函数。
every page and at the range.
那么你的问题是什么？
And so what was your question?
我想是，
I guess,
如果你在设置了 satp 之后，
it's does walks still work
walk 仍然是一样的方式工作吗。
the same way if you call it after satp
是啊，怎么了。
is set. Yeah why.
能够成功的原因是
Why we work out the reason
内核页表设置是恒等映射。
it work out the kernel set up in identity mapping.
好的，对。
Ok, right, right.
非常重要，
Very important,
非常好的问题，
very good question,
很多事情都解决了，
a lot of things just happened
因为实际上设置了恒等映射。
to work out because actually the identity mapping is set up.
我明白了，我想这是有道理的。
I see, I think that makes sense,
我有一个简短的问题。
I have a quick question.
所有进程的 satp 寄存器存储在哪，
Where the satp register stored for all of the processes.
每个内核只有一个 satp ，
There only one satp per core,
但是在每一个程序结构中。
but in every proc structure.
如果你看一下 proc.h ,
If you look at proc.h, there is,
有一个指向页表的指针，在这。
a pointer to the page table,
好的，理解了。
here, here. okay, makes sense.
另外，
And also with regards to the
关于三个页表，
three page tables are like the
可以组成完整的地址，
three tables that can complete the
甚至
full address and help you get
可以帮助你获得一些东西的完整地址，
a full address for even something,
这比拥有一个巨大的页表
how does how is that better
有什么更好的地方，
I guess than than having one
我并没有真正完全理解。
giant page table I didn't really
这是一个很好的问题，
fully understand what. A great question,
原因是在自由级别的页面表中，
the reason is because in the free level page table,
你可以将许多条目留空。
you can leave a lot of entries empty.
例如，如果
So, for example if you leave
你将顶层页表中的条目直接留空，
the entry in the top level page table directly empty,
则根本不必
you don't have to create middle
为这些条目创建
level page tables or bottom level
中层页表或底层页表。
page tables at all, for those entries.
这意味着
Like this means like a big
整个虚拟地址空间的一大块
[] of the whole virtual address
根本不需要任何映射。
space doesn't have to have any mapping at all.
好的，好的。
Okay, okay.
你不需要表，
You don't have the table there,
它根本不存在。
it just doesn't exist.
我明白了，
I see,
基本上这些块
basically allocating these chunks on demand
是按数量和类型分配的，
as volumes and types,
好的，理解了。
OK that makes sense,
是的，
Yeah you're starting basically with three
从三页开始，
page three pages namely,
一个高层的，
one from the top level one
一个中间的，
for, one intermediate one from,
一个底层的。
one bottom level.
然后，
And then,
随着操作的进行，
as you go you create more
你将创建更多的页表目录。
page table directories.
好的，好的，
Okay, okay,
太好了，太感谢你了。
cool, thank you so much.
不用谢。
You're welcome.
还有什么问题吗。
Any more questions.
我有一个问题，
I'm sorry I have another one,
它真的很小，
it's really really small but
在 vm.c 的 43 ， 41 行，
in the vm.c on line 43, 41,
写到，不，或许是 43 行，
it says that, no, might 43, my bad,
有一个 PHYSTOP-(uint64)etext ，但是会不会
it says 'PHYSTOP-(uint64)etext', but wouldn't that,
访问到
would not go over the, I guess the memory that
我们不应该接触的内存，
we shouldn't touch, I don't
我不知道这是否有意义，
know if that makes sense,
但是，会不会这样。
but, would that go.
我想我不明白，
I guess I don't understand, would
他们会不会检查一下空闲内存。
they go over free memory.
不，我不这么认为，
No, I don't think so,
KERNBASE 是 0x8000 ，对吧，
so KERNBASE is 0x8000, right
所以这是内存的开始。
so that's the beginning of memory.
内核在那里，
Kernel sits there in,
基本上，这是一个大小，
basically, this thing is a size,
所以 etext 是内核的最后一个地址，
right, so etext is the last address of the kernel,
减去 KERNBASE ，
subtract KERNBASE, that basically gives
它给出了内核的大小，以字节为单位。
you the size of the kernel, in byte.
而且，你知道，我不知道它有多少，
And, you know, I don't know how
但它大概是 60 或 90 页，
much it is, but it's like you know 60 or 90
或差不多大小。
pages or something like that.
所以这个映射
And so this map
是内核的文本部分。
is basically the text part of the kernel.
嗯，还有足够的空间。
Um, and there's enough space.
那里有足够的 DRAM 来映射内核文本。
There's enough DRAM there to map that the kernel text.
我不确定，我是否回答了你的问题，但是。
I'm not sure, I'm answering your question,
我想我明白了。
but. I think, I think I understand.
我以为 etext 是从别的地方开始的，
I thought that etext starts
好的，我想我现在明白了，谢谢。
somewhere else, okay, I think I understand now, thank you.
所以 etext 是最后一条指令，
So etext basically the last instruction,
内核最后一条指令的地址。
the address of the last instruction of the kernel.
好的，好的。
Okay, okay.